Orthodox Christianity for today's world. You are listening to Ancient Faith Radio.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and he
will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled. All who
dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate
with song The Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
even to young. Host this live
Colin show focused on enchantment
in creation. The union of the scene
and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout
history. Welcome to the Lord of
Spirits. Good evening, giant
killers. Man, I can't believe I
messed up my my praise there. I
don't know. Giant killers, dragon
slayers, bat people. You're listening
to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Michael, because he don't hinder
gender. You can do those other things to those other.
Dolly noted. My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young, editor-in-chief of the Etten Moors, is
with me straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana, and I'm Father Andrew Stephen
Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, three square miles of glory, purchased precariously at
top the arcane tire of podcasting, hovering dozens of stories about a disused gateway to
the underworld former crematorium and relive. And if you are listening to us live, you can
call us at 855-237-2346 and you can talk to us.
This is not an all Q&A episode tonight.
We're actually covering some pre-planned content.
We'll get to your calls in just a minute,
the beginning of our second half,
and Mike need flanned again.
We'll be taking your calls.
So what happened to Trudy?
They're giving us the trainees now.
A Trudy's been promoted.
Trudy's in charge of the...
All the more reason.
We should have her as the a-lister of this.
on our on our spot here. I think Trudy got a life. She doesn't want to be with us at at nights
anymore, you know. So that's where it is. You're gonna be okay? I don't know. It's depressing.
So we just we just finished kind of breaking her in in terms of our right.
wacky morning show antics, you know, and now feel a little abandoned. Is this the first time you've
pet feelings on the
video. It's not even no, it's not feelings. It's not. Okay. Okay. It's just checking. You know, it's just kind of, you know.
It's all right. Now we now we got to, you know, break in this Mike deadpan guy or bedpan or whatever his name is.
Yeah. I know. I know. Are we are we safe? Is this like an unpromotable guy? Like I mean, he's going nowhere in life. So he's
Staple assume we'll have him for the rest of the show's run. I could be I mean
Of course, you know, how long is this so really going to run?
You know, who know?
This could be the last episode right now.
It could be.
It absolutely could be.
Before we begin.
It'd be weird, given what you're about to talk about, but possible last episode.
In case you people haven't heard, the Lord of Spirits conference is going to be back for
its second manifestation this October 2nd through 5th, 2025, at the Antiochine Village in
and ligand your Pennsylvania featuring none other than our barriones.
Reverend Dr. Swampo Grimself, the very Reverend Dr. Joseph Lucas of Miami, Richard Roughty,
Roughty Rollin and your humble servant. You can get your tickets at ancientfate.com slash events.
And I recommend everybody get those tickets quickly because I think there's only like 40 rooms or
so left at the Antioch in Village, which means that close to 60% are currently taken. Now we will
have commuter tickets for people who don't get rooms at the Village, but there is a max and we did
Did it hit it last?
year. So yeah, get your tickets. This could well be the very last time. And we're super
not getting about that. It probably will be the last conference we do last year.
It's very well. Yeah, because my demands to do each one continue to escalate. So we just
have to budget. Yeah. We don't have a budget for like another two-story cake that, you
know a group of finished fuseliers pop out of the second private
for my dogs. Right. I mean they're heathen dogs. You can't baptize them. They're forever pagans.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. That's why they need their own separate jet. I understand. Yeah. Don't want
to contaminate them. Right. So everybody, remember our episode that we did? I think this was in,
was this in year two or year three? I'm turning remember now. It was pretty moderately. I'm not
a circle man. I don't know. Yeah. Moderately early on, it was called the priest shall make a
tone meant that was the one with with the goats. So we're talking about
Toneman again tonight, but we're picking back up with our series on apocrypha and we're
looking specifically at the text called the apocalypse of Abraham.
So father, I assume this is about how Abraham is causing the end of the world, because
isn't that what apocalypse means?
Well, that that depends.
If someone in the past sees and knows about the end of the world, is there some implied causation
there?
Yeah, no it
about how Abraham became a zombie.
Um, zombie Abraham had, wait, I don't know, I have to work out the lurch for that as we
go on as you were.
Yeah, I feel like, see, that song is a good example of what where I feel like they had kind
of a catchy hook, right?
I already read many sons, many sons had father Abraham and then like they kind of didn't
know where to go with it.
They're like, well, I'm one of them.
So are you?
And then you get to the, so let's just praise the Lord.
and then click on the button.
clearly ran out of like steam right.
I mean, what's it for us at
the kiosk beginning?
Like what do you do after that?
Like let's just praise the Lord, guys.
You know, it's sort of like when
the lead singer runs out of lyrics.
So it just sort of goes over and poses
next to the guitar player,
Turgus Solo.
And it's like, check this guy out.
The children's praise song equivalent.
I feel.
Yeah, but the apocalypse of Abraham, which is probably everybody's second favorite piece
of slow, melodic preserve, topography.
Right.
After second in it.
Yeah.
Um, I mean, we'll do.
I think that's a right.
Like, yeah, so we're going to second in it.
Somebody will do first in it.
That's right.
even in this series since it's all we talk about all that I heard that as well. Yes, that's what I've
been told. But so, yes, the apocalypse of Abraham is a piece of anachic literature even though it's
not the apocalypse of Enic. And so the anachic literature, we've talked about other things that are
part of the Inakik literature like we did our episode on the Book of Jubiles.
which is an occipital literature, even though again,
it's not one of the numbered books of Enek
and Enek is not even especially prominent in it,
it's written from the perspective of Moses on Mount Sinai.
And so when we talk about an occipital literature,
we're not really talking about just stuff about Enek.
We're talking about, and yes,
I will continue to pronounce it Enek.
I don't care what people think.
I like Land of the Lost, what can I say?
But at Arctic literature, we're talking about literature
in the Second Temple period that deals with
a certain set of themes,
certain topics and themes
that don't necessarily involve Enoch himself.
So the Enoch and Enoch and Enoch literature
is really referring to the book of First Enoch,
not the person of Enoch.
Yeah.
So, the book of first scenic is a piece of second-templar Jewish literature.
It's apocalyptic.
It deals with particular themes related to the giants and a zeal, really, are probably
the two primary things.
So the book of Jubilee has a bunch of material dealing with the giants and Noah and the
flood.
That's why it tends to get categorized as an ocular literature in the case.
of the apocalypse of Abraham, it's going to be because of a zeal showing up. And there's a,
I don't know if it made it into the YouTube thumbnail, but the advertisers for tonight's episode,
we had a lovely woodcut of a zeal. I know you never look, but yes, our YouTube thumbnail not only
has that wood cut but it also says apocalyptic goat demon. Oh there you go.
Yeah, you're welcome. And that that woodcut I think is pretty metal. That's all I'm saying it is
so
but
Yeah, so so it's a zeal that is appearance and is prominent to the apocalypse of Abraham
And the fact that it is a piece of apocalyptic literature
That causes the apocalypse of Abraham to be classified as an apocalyptic literature even though
that I know people are going to get less excited. The apocalypse.
of Abraham does not really deal expressly with giants.
I'm just like that, Sankin.
Now that the disappointment is washed over you all, there is other
interesting stuff, though, about the apocalypse of Abraham.
So this is like most of the second temple Jewish literature, the
second temple text that we've talked about on the show.
And in this series, what that was not preserved within Judaism.
So rabbinic Judaism did not keep copies of the apocalypse of Abraham.
You ask a rabbi about the apocalypse of Abraham.
They're probably not going to know what you're talking about unless they studied this in
the binocular. Right. And so it wasn't preserved.
in Jewish circles, it was preserved in Christian circles, but like some of the texts we've talked about,
like the Testament of the 12 patriarchs where we've got manuscripts in Christian monasteries
like on Mount Athos and Marisaba monastery, this one was not necessarily preserved in Orthodox
Christian circles.
Yeah, it only ends up, well we'll talk about them, but one particular heretical group in the Balkans.
Yes.
And so the copies we have of it are in Slavonic and their medieval Slavonic manuscripts.
They're medieval Slavonic manuscripts that were being used by this heretical sect that we're
going to talk a little bit more about in a minute here. So that said, if the only copies we have
or
medieval and in Slavonic, why would anybody think that this is actually a Jewish text? Let
a load of second-tabled Jewish text, right? It's more likely be a, some text come up with by this
sect. Right. How do we know it's not? Well, there's a couple of ways we know it's not.
So one of the things is just the genre and the type of literature it is in the way it reads.
There are a number of touch points with other second-templed Jewish literature.
But a big giveaway is that there are a bunch of Semitic names, like a say-zel,
but not limited to that.
Semitic names that come from a Semitic language that are translated directly into Sloponic.
So what do I mean by that? Well, okay, so if you think about the Old Testament, most of
the names we know for Old Testament figures and even a lot of New Testament figures come
to us from the Latin name.
No.
Which is a Latin from Greek from Hebrew, so it's gone through a...
you hops. So we talk about Moses, not about Moisha, right? Right. And we talk about Elijah,
right? Yeah. Unless you're around Greeks, right? You talk about Elias. But even that is from
Elias, which is from Eliahu.
Right.
Yeah.
So it's gone through.
And every time it goes through these names, it gets transformed.
I think it gets transformed more like the name Louis or Louis is actually from Elijah.
Wait, really?
Isn't it?
Yes.
Ludovicus on ultimately.
Ludovic.
It's just it's just gone through a couple more from Aliyah.
They say so.
He says right.
He says a couple more transformations or James from Oh, I mean, let's not talk about James.
Yeah.
But so there's these these transfer wrong and winding road there. And so you could tell and
You may have had you know if you've been in an orthodox church for matins or vespers or something where they're they're doing the things
For an Old Testament say and they're using the Greek translations. You probably didn't know who they were talking about
Like there's this stuff about Elias and Alicias
You know which in English are more commonly known as Elijah and Alisha
Yeah.
But that's going back a step.
But so in this case, you have names like Azale, Yehoals,
and other we're going to talk about some others that have just gone straight
from a Semitic language into Slavonic.
They haven't passed through Greek because we know what happens to those names
when they go through Greek.
Because we have like Greek translations of the Old Testament, for example.
And other texts we have that are like of the church fathers or of course the Bible itself in
Slavonic, right? We can see how things go from Greek to Slavonic. And these days go direct
from a Semitic language. So that Semitic language is probably Aramaic, some dialect of Aramaic.
That's hard to demonstrate.
Right, like.
approve because we have this we have this gap. So we could tell from these features of the text,
yeah, this was probably written in some dialect of Aramaic. But we don't have any Aramaic manuscripts,
we don't have any textual evidence to trace, we don't know exactly where the text came from that
ended up in the Balkans in the Middle Ages. Yeah, I mean, I mean, this is characteristic of a lot of
these kinds of...
texts that they only exist in a translation.
You know, we just don't have the older version.
I mean, most texts from the ancient world did not survive.
We only have a minority of them, a little minority probably.
Yeah.
Um, so, so we can't trace that.
And that means we also can't trace where it came from like to come up through
Syria.
There's some air, American, air, American traditions in Georgia.
I like that it come through there.
where the whole history of the text is kind of untraceable at this point.
But in terms of when we would date, so that means we've got to take a lot of relative
features of the text and that kind of thing to try and figure out how far back this would
date from.
And so while it conforms to a lot of tropes and things in other Second Table Jewish literature,
especially other
or anachic literature for the second temple period.
There are no explicitly Christian references.
So what I mean by that is like we did an episode
where we talked about the ascension of Isaiah.
And at the ascension of Isaiah, there were a couple chapters
added that were kind of really on the nose.
Obviously, Christian.
Right.
Where it was sort of like Jesus.
This was fulfilled when Jesus did this and this and this.
Right?
Right. Right. Right. Really, you know, Christians kind of improving on the text, which yeah, it sounds crazy to us now, but was completely a normal thing back in the day. Yeah. Yeah.
There's nothing like that in this text. Right. Not even there's not even anything that we could really tell for sure came from the heretical sect that was using it.
In this sense that right. Oh, this is explicitly one of the doctrines they taught right being laid out here.
There's not that really either.
Which strongly suggests that it was pretty well preserved.
Yeah.
From its original status.
Right.
And so, based on some things, at a certain point here, later this first half, when we're
talking about the contents, we'll get into a little deeper on why.
But it's generally dated to somewhere toward the end of the first century AD, probably
around 80, AD 80.
shortly after the destruction of the Temple in Jerusalem.
from a Jewish non-Christian Jewish writer.
Yeah, which that destruction was in the year 70 for those who don't remember.
Right.
Yeah.
So those things I take for granted, but that's because I've spent too much time studying
the New Testament.
But yeah.
So we've been mentioning this heretical Balkan sect who we're talking about are the
Boga meals.
I know it has the best name or I prefer this
like
the pronunciation, bogemille. Well, I see, I say bogemille because it's like you bought a meal
and now you get one free. Oh, yeah, yeah.
And you know how much I like to get things free. Thank you. Big Dutch. So yeah, the bogemille's
had a pretty good run of it as a heretical sect.
Yeah, they were around for about 500 years.
So and they were roughly like in the region called Macedonia.
Now we're going to get a bunch of calls.
Oh, yeah, Macedonia.
You're agreeing the Greeks.
Yeah, but also a lot of a lot of the former Yugoslavia.
So Bosnia hurts a govindia.
Right.
Exactly.
Like, yeah, Croatia.
I mean, it was it was basically I think at the time is basically Bulgarian Empire that region essentially Bulgarian Empire
Yeah, so but that area right yeah, they're around for about 500 years
When we get into their beliefs you you'll see why they're kind of hard to stamp out
So they they come into being somewhere around 9.50
And generally in part of the region referred to as Macedonia, but we're not totally sure.
We're not even absolutely sure who the founder was.
There are a couple of figures who were sort of regarded as saints sort of equivalent by
the Boga Beels because they did miracles and stuff who were associated with the beginning
of the Sacked By.
It's not totally clear if either of them or both or neither were the actual historical founders of it.
Whether they were just early famous adherents of it, right, who did things.
And then it was finally stamped out in 1463, which you may notice is like 10 years after the fall of Constantinople,
because yes, that's when the Turks reached Bosnia.
Yeah.
any kind of got rid of a number of groups that they were not unborn.
And the Turks just killed them all.
Yes.
So those that were left, I mean, I don't think there were a lot left at that point.
No, no, well, the tur- as the Turks moved through, they had been- they've been persecuted
by the Christian church too, but the Turks were just slaughtering them, right, as they
went.
They had no use for them.
And we'll see why.
Here's the talk.
the release a little bit, but because they're extinct, that's part of the reason why we don't,
right? We have texts like this, like the apocalypse of Abraham that were preserved,
but the apocalypse of Abraham wasn't written by them. We just know they used it.
You know, so it's not like we have a lot of firsthand like, oh here's our
our ins, Boga Meal Insider perspective on Boga Meal history, right?
We don't have that.
Really? Right. What we do have about them is all written by non-bogamials, right?
Talking about them. And then we have some texts that were used by them, but not
necessarily written by them. So we have to kind of conjecture how they made use of
them. So, but the Boga Meals represented pretty much bog standard dosticism. Yeah.
Like, if you're at all familiar with dust.
in the second and third and four centuries AD,
this is just a 10th to 15th century
sort of reflowering of the same kind of ideas.
That being, you know, premise number one,
the material creation was created by the devil
or by an evil god.
They seem to ever find their marcinas in the little
it so that it's not just a straight dualism of good God, evil God or the Old Testament
God being the evil God, but they still had the material creation being created by the devil.
Whereas the spiritual world that was created by the actual God is sort of holy and pure.
And so based on that you get all of the anti-material, anti-worldly, kind of
of nostic theological stuff that you would expect.
And one of those things, which is part of what makes this hard, and what made it hard to get rid of them for a while,
is that they rejected any idea of an institutional church.
So they didn't have any kind of ordination.
Yeah, I mean, a lot of their deal is, it's funny like they reject institutional church, they reject civil authorities.
they
you know, they reject sacraments.
It's interesting.
I mean, this is kind of a,
I'm not gonna say that they're exactly the same.
Just say Adabaptus.
As Protestants.
But, or certainly,
I will not all pro-
Radical Reformations.
Yeah.
But, but there's, it's interesting.
There's a certain list of things
that they're on board with that are the same as this.
You know, and this is this feeling that keeps cropping up
over church history.
You know, a step.
churches always have some group like this that kind of reacts against them and comes out from them.
And so you have these figures, like I referred to those two, one of them is an impeter, and I can't
remember the name of the other one. But they're just sort of charismatic figures. Yeah.
Who are part of this act? They don't have any official, they don't have bishops, they don't have
priests, they don't have ministers or pastors or any kind of clergy, they don't have any kind of
sacraments. It's very
much sort of a spirituality, right, and a set of
mystical, mainly mystical practices
that people were participating in.
So they face persecution, you know,
in Orthodox and Roman Catholic countries
were being sort of both political dissidents
and religious dissidents and heretics, right.
But the Turks, when they came in and took over, their rule number one is you're now going
to submit to Turkish rule.
And so people like the Boga meals who said no, we submit to no human.
That wasn't popular with the Turks in the 15th century.
Yeah, it wasn't like some of the weird Russian sects that could just run off into the wilderness
and people like, no, we're not going to chase you.
over seven time zones. Go ahead. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, you know, they took Constantinople,
but the Orthodox, including the patriarch, right, you can use the patriarch to help cover
in your Christian subjects. Yeah. Right. Your Christian subjects will generally,
right, to submit to the civil authorities. Right. So that's a different case.
The Boga meals are the other way. They're like, no, we're not going to listen to you. Right.
Like yeah, yeah, there's no leadership for them to co-opt right
So that left one sort of solution to that problem.
And that's why they got wiped out.
Now that's sad.
So the apocalypse of Abraham is a text
that was used by this essentially Nostek sect.
But, this is kind of a footnote,
but I know I never do those, but this is kind of a footnote,
But...
St. Epiphanias of Solomonus.
We've I know we've mentioned before on the show author of the bread box. Yes, the panoron. Yes
We're in the page and saint of the second edition of the orthodoxy and heterodoxy, which was released on his feast day
Well, there we go. Yes, not on purpose. It just worked out that way
Do you fancy yourself or a feater of heresies while they're in here?
Um.
I don't know. I'm nice. I'm way nicer than St. Epiphanios. I mean go read his stuff people. I mean he just doesn't hold back.
Or do you fancy yourself in general or are you just fancy?
I do like fancy coffees. There you go. You're a fancy lad. I think.
I wasn't going to go that far. Okay.
So we'll have to find out what we need to do is ask your dad to see if he's got a picture of you dressed like blue boy.
Right.
No, so we're at home.
Thank God that doesn't exist.
But so but say to have a audience of the
Praudariate was he did refute a series of
heresies, including a bunch of forms of
nozzlesism from the original era of
nozzlesism. And then there he describes a
gnostic text called the Apocalypse of Abraham.
Yeah, same name, but probably not the same
text as well. But as far as we could tell,
not the same tech.
because the way he describes it is not does not describe this text, right?
Something else. Right. So yeah. So he describes, oh, they have this text in da da da da
and the da da da da da da and the salovonic text we have, do not match at all.
And as we said, there's seems to be good evidence that this was translated
directly into Slavonic from some Semitic language.
of a funny sort of been looking at would have been in Greek. Yeah. So you can't
well, was there some Greek version of this? Is it a whole other text? Is it related to this?
Frankly, we don't know. I mean, we did just we have no evidence we don't know. All we know for sure
is that the text saying epiphaneos describes that he was looking at at the text we have in
Slavonic are clearly not the same text. Yeah. There's no way to determine if there's some kind of
relationship between the two.
Other.
than the title. But this happens a lot. Remember what we talked about the the assumption of Moses.
We talked about how when you start digging around in the church fathers, they refer to a testament of
Moses and an assumption of Moses. And it's not clear if they're the same book. I mean, this
happens a lot, right? Because you see ancient authors referring to the title of a book and then we
find a book somewhere with the same
or a similar title, it's easy to just assume,
oh, this must be the exact same book,
but often it's not queer, right?
This is a common occurrence
that the relationship between the two is actually not so clear.
So all that said about where we got this text.
And it is important that we point out
that it's preserved by the Mogawils, right?
That it's preserved by this heretical sect
Because
Because when we're looking at the teaching of this, there's a difference with the, when
we talked about the Testament of Abraham, for example, that's been preserved at Mount
Athos, right?
And Marseille, a monastery.
And it's among the Nancy Scrolls, right?
That means the fact that Christian monks were copying this over and over and over again
for century after century after century to preserve it was obviously it's not scripture.
weren't reading from it liturgyly.
But that was sort of an endorsement of the contents. I thought there's something valuable here that we need to preserve
In terms of the interpretation and understanding of the scriptures that's presented here, right?
So this was not preserved in that way
So we are not looking at the apocalypse of Abraham and from the perspective of oh
Here's a summary of
Early Christian tradition about anything
Okay. But through this heretical sect having preserved it, we have this text that gives
us a window back to around AD 80 to a Jewish writer and how he looked at things and how
he thought about things, right, the world and events in the world and the scriptures,
gives us a window back in time to that point. And that's why we're talking about it and
how we're gonna use it tonight as we...
talk about it is here's how people were thinking around the time the New
Testaments being written. Yeah, yeah, yeah, right. There's some Jewish people
were thinking around the time the New Testament was being written.
Because because we're in mind, we're talking in the first century, especially.
But in the century or two before, and probably I don't know, maybe even more
than that, it's really Judaism's. Right. Yeah, there's a lot of different
years, a lot of different groups. There's no Pope of Judaism saying this.
This is what everybody has to do.
So this is, this represents a Judaism or at least one person, you know, right there of
you.
How sub Jewish people thought and remember the author, all the authors of the New Testament
are second temple Jews and Christianity is a Judaism.
Yeah.
In the first century, a D, right?
It is one of the 40s.
Judaism.
Yeah.
So we'll see there are so you could see some connections in thought between.
the original author of this Jewish author of this text in the first century, and some of the New Testament authors
We'll see as as we go and how they were thinking about things
The Boga meals just is the favor of preserving the text right without reference to them right and there weird doctrines so
The text actually begins sort of in Abraham's youth
Thank you.
There are a lot of stories in Jewish tradition about Abraham's youth because when you're reading
through Genesis, you get the story of the Tower of Babel and then you get the story of Abraham
with no time marker whatsoever.
Yeah, how much time has passed?
How old is he?
If any, is this even after the Tower of Babel?
Yeah.
Is he living during the time of the Tower of Babel?
suggest that sort of my
of the proximity but there are Jewish traditions to that effect, right? And so that fact that we're
just kind of dropped in on Abraham and that when we're dropped in on him, God has chosen him
for this whole thing, right? He's living in Orr, living on the pagans of the biggest city of the
world during the Sumerian Renaissance and God just boom, right, has already picked him. And so
So you get a lot of traditions developing about, well,
had God picked him out of all the people in the world at the time. And what had happened
earlier in his life, and how did his life relate to the Tower of Bable and what was going
on there, right? It raises all these questions. And those questions generated a variety
of traditions that aren't, they can't totally be merged with each other, right? They're
It's one of these strands gets preserved here.
And...
The probably the big distinguishing feature of that at the beginning of the apocalypse of Abraham is Abraham's father Tara, who is presented as an idol maker by trade.
Yeah, which in Genesis, it's pretty clear that he's an idolater and that he's a pagan, but this is kind of taking several steps further than that.
Right. Well, it's fairly clear, it's Genesis.
Yeah.
There's the them stopping in Iran, which if you know about the moon god makes sense.
But also there's a reference in Joshua.
With Joshua is giving his sort of final.
So he talks about how Abraham's family were idolaters.
But yeah, there's an episode between being an idolater and being a professional idol maker.
That's sort of next level.
So as I don't make it, there's
to sort of dispute that breaks out between him and Abraham,
his son who's being kind of a smart,
alicky kid, that's where Tara is trying to teach him
about the making of idols.
And as explaining to him how when you make an idol,
that idol sort of embodies one of these spiritual powers
or forces in the world, right?
like the storm or like, you know.
take your pick, God of whatever, right? And how we've talked about idolatry on the show, right?
That it's now embodied in this idol, and so can be manipulated, worshiped, etc, etc, etc.
Right? And he's trying to teach this to his son, Abraham. Abraham, however, sort of rejoinders,
that well, all of those powers you list are opposed to one another.
Yeah, which is, you know, basically...
It's basically a good first century philosophical argument, because one of the big concerns is,
well, there has to be something above everything, or something that starts everything.
Right.
Nothing could be ultimate, because they all have some opposite.
You've got this God who brings a plentiful harvest.
You've got this other God who brings famine.
God, you know, this God who people look to.
to be healed of maladies. You have this other god like Reshef that you know brings plague.
Yeah, so I mean not only does it present that kind of philosophical side but also this participates in
the standard biblical polemic against paganism which is these guys are a bunch of small weak
spirits that can't deliver. Right and in the stories that are constructed around which pagan
good worship is constructed.
These gods are all opposed to each other and fighting and at odds with each other.
So like a pagan can't really deny that even beyond just the philosophical side.
Right?
Like, yeah.
You know, you look, you even look at like Persephone, right?
And the meter you have this opposition between demeter and the Hades, right?
Like, yeah.
There's always a pushing forces.
So there must be some other god who's actually the first principle who is above.
And who made all of these others?
Yeah, right? And again, notice this is worth the biblical version of quote unquote monotheism
Right, right?
There are multiple gods, but then one most high god
Who unlike the big and most high gods is the actual creator god of everything in his omnipotent
Right who is the god of gods? Right. Yeah
Who all those powers serve in worship as we're reminded over and over again in liturgy
Yeah, yeah
And so God sort of resolves this dispute between father and son by sending fire from heaven
that roasts and kills Tara and blows up his idle shop and destroys everything.
Yeah.
That's proving that Abraham was right.
So, um, it doesn't totally conform to the biblical story of Abraham, but, yeah.
basically comparable.
Yeah, you think that if that really happened, it would have been mentioned though in the Bible.
I don't know, but yeah, I mean, it seems like a key event.
Yeah.
Like, it only kind of dying at Harron.
Right, right, right.
Um, I mean, I have a question, I have a question.
So do you think that stuff like this is on some level self consciously fiction?
you know, like, like, okay, I know it didn't turn out this way.
But for the sake of our story, I'm going to write it this way to kind of make my point
about idolatry.
Well, I know I'm asking to speculate, but that's a very modern question.
Okay.
Yeah.
You're told a story.
Did that really happen?
Sure.
Right.
Like, so I don't think, especially when you're talking about something that's ancient
history at the time it's being told.
Yeah, thousands of years before.
Right. You're trying to communicate something with that story like, is every word of it
quote unquote literally true? Like there's not even a way to ask that question in most
ancient languages.
Yeah, so I think it probably just comes down to like, what are their expectations for
these different kinds of texts?
Right.
You know, and this text is not trying to be anything other than what it is, which is a
a certain kind of commentary on the Bible.
in some level. Right. Which it's a certain type of question. Right. And I know what I say this,
there's people out there who like fight it hard to believe. Well, how could they not have asked that question?
Right. Well, there's lots of questions you don't ask when you hear a story.
Like every year I read the parable of the Good Samaritan. Okay. Nobody ever interrupts me and asks,
What was his name?
Right?
I mean, that's a perfectly valid question.
Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
But right, if someone actually did interrupt me and asked that, that would be a sign that
like they didn't understand what was happening with me telling this story.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right?
Or where was this?
You know, like, that's, yeah.
And those are questions about facticity, right?
Like...
So, yeah, these were understood to sort of function in this way.
So this is communicating to you something about idolatry,
something about paganism,
something about the difference between Abraham
and the other people in the world during Abraham's life.
Yeah, even his dad.
Right, including his own family.
Yeah.
So it's communicating those things, right?
and asking those other questions.
At that time would have just been taken to be like missing the point.
They would have looked at you.
Do you really not get what we're talking about here?
Like yeah.
Yeah.
And of course there's no way to ask a question like, well, what if you had a time machine or what if you had a video camera because there were neither of those ideas right.
In existence.
And even the word real.
Right? Like, did that really happen? What do you mean real?
Yeah. Like, when a video camera have picked it up and
what it have looked exactly this way, like, are those the exact words that
that person said? No more and no less, right? Like, those questions,
those questions aren't really getting it.
not understanding how writing and storytelling and communication happened in the ancient world.
And that's why I'm pretty I would prefer that that's why people with these various traditions weren't
concerned with the fact that they kind of contradict each other. Right so someone could tell this
story about Terra and then someone else could talk about them trying to throw Abraham into a brick furnace
while they were building the tower.
of Bavle because he wouldn't worship idols. And I don't think if you ask someone who
is familiar with both of those traditional stories, I think if he said to those contradict
each other, they would have said no. Yeah, because they're not trying to do.
They're communicating the same thing about relationship between Abraham and his idolatrous
society. Yeah. Right. Even though we would say, well, no, one of those must be true and
one of those wasp falls.
Um, um, at least they could both be false, but they can't both be true. Right. Insert any modern person talking about the four
Gospels. Right. Was there one angel or two angels? What are these is a lie? Um, so yeah, 50% of Legion and this guy 50% yeah. Yeah.
So, yeah, so that's just a miss.
And again, I know it's hard for us as modern people to not think like modern people, right?
Not ask the questions we ask because those are the questions we've been brought up and
taught to ask, right?
But we have to accept one of the basic steps of humility in general is accepting the fact
to that other people, even other people who live in the world you do at the same time and in
relatively the same place.
See things very differently than you do.
And that doesn't mean that you're right
and they're all wrong.
Right?
Like, that's just a basic aspect of humility.
Let alone people who live in radically different times
in places and cultures, right?
Yeah.
We're gonna see things differently than you.
And you asserting, well no mine is right.
And you know, they're all wrong is not, right?
It's arrogant. We'll just leave it at that.
So after that terror rising moment, oh, you didn't even get how that's a dig in the
crates reference. You didn't get the half of it.
That's okay.
Someone out there did. I'm confident after that one reference I made that somebody got
Like, uh, to idiot box?
like I'm convinced now no reference I could make is too obscure. So what out there gets every one of them.
Not the same person, but
you ever meet somebody who's getting all of them.
That'd be I'll be deeply disturbed and take it as a challenge.
So after that, there's side of kind of a smash cut. So we move into another thing.
there's sort of three pieces to the apocalypse.
of Abraham, that sort of piece one, piece two has to do with Abraham being brought to
Mount Horib to make a sacrifice, not Isaac in this case, right?
So this is not telling the story of Abraham's potential sacrifice of Isaac.
This is a different sacrifice, and this sacrifice looks suspiciously like the day of a tonement.
There are goats involved. Now again, maybe going, well, wait a second. The day of atonement
doesn't exist until Leviticus 16. Abraham is back in Genesis. Why would he be doing
a day of atonement thing? Well, we'll get to that. Yes. Right. But this is another one
of those, you know, is this asserting a literal time? Is this asserting that Abraham practiced
the day of atonement.
like really as a historical fact.
I mean, the answer that's basically no,
but also that's a misunderstanding
of what the text is doing.
So there are goats involved, right?
But so Abraham in this has sort of a guide
who's helping him.
Yeah, which is, I mean, this is pretty standard
for apocalypse is there's always a psychopath.
But in this case, the psychopath is...
also a priest who is helping him and is also a jealous being of some type.
Yes, with a very suspicious name, that being Yehoa, which means Yahweh God.
Right, that's the name of this being.
So that's odd, right?
Unless you consider, right, so for example, in the Torah, when we
see the angel of the Lord introduced who's going to lead Israel and who
adds up leading Israel through the Exodus, through the wilderness, through the
conquest, and then leaves at the beginning of the book of judges. Right. What God
says will identify the angel of the Lord is that God will place his name in
him.
So here we have this angelic being who bears the name of God.
Right, Yahweh, Hashem, right, the name, right, is placed upon him.
And so this is an instance, the Apocalypse of Abraham, and from its author in the
1st century AD of what we've talked about before on the show, this idea of a second
power in heaven, right, that there is a being who is visible, who interacts with people
who has a bodily form, who is Yahweh, but who is distinguished from Yahweh, the
the God of Israel who came.
cannot be seen and have you live afterwards.
Yeah. And I mean, within a Christian context, see John chapter one, identifying this figure
as Jesus of Nazareth. But in this text, which is not a Christian text, you're not going
to get that.
Right. You don't get that second part.
Right. And the fact that you don't get that is again, like I said, this is why we know
there are direct Christian elements where somebody's come in and kind of said, ah, and
That is, you know.
Yeah.
But so he's dressed like a
Levitical priest
When he shows up
In white with a golden sat
So the idea is that this being also has some kind of heavenly priesthood
and so
This heavenly priest is now going to...
sort of walk Abraham through how to do this, this ritual sacrifice and
to make this sort of even more direct a zeal who's sort of mentioned in the day of atonement ritual.
Right, the one goat is for Yahweh, the other goat is for a zeal. A zeal also shows up in person.
Hmm, so Yahweh the God of Israel shows up in person in the person of Yeho'el.
and Azazel shows up in person for...
as this sort of giant ugly raven thing.
And that raven form, is it just because like ravens are black
and they're cool, man. It's got.
It's a reference to, remember, we talked about this on the show
before, we were talking about covenants. When Abraham did the covenant ritual
and he cut the animals in half and split them in half.
Yeah, and all that.
he was waiting for God to arrive. He had to shoe the birds away.
Right. So they're kind of getting in the way of from the carcasses. Yeah.
So they were trying to sort of disrupt. So the reason he appears as a raven is as
Azels here to kind of disrupt this sacrificial ritual. Later on he transforms into his dragon form.
This is final form?
I don't know.
I mean, I think no. I think this is actually his original form.
Yeah, I mean, it's interesting because especially interesting because like usually his
azale was just referred to as being out there somewhere.
Right.
You know, and here he is like ready to rumble.
And like in the, I mean, you see him in in first genic, like scheming with the other rebel
angels and stuff, right?
Yeah.
But he's not like manifesting like this, right?
Yeah, but so he manifests in this dragon form which is we're going to see a little later in the text of the apocalypse of Abraham
is presenting him as
the serpent that shows up in Genesis
Right the dragon right so this is dragon being used the same way it's used in the in the book of Revelation
Right to refer to that priority old
Right being the devil
So this
a tonement sacrificial ritual that Abraham is doing here is sort of this
section is apocalyptic also in that it's sort of presenting okay here's sort of
the spiritual reality that's going on with the idea of atonement okay right
because your average israelite or judaite or judian
who went to the day of Atomit ritual, like didn't see a dragon fighting and right, like
it would be not right.
What?
Visually, right.
It wouldn't have increased attendance, but they didn't actually, you know, like directly
see that, right?
But Abraham is sort of directly seeing that.
Right, right.
Like this is what's really going on.
Yeah.
You know, which I mean, this is like, I mean, this is like the apocalypse of John is sort of
showing you what's really going
going on, you know, from this higher, on this higher level,
right in terms of, you know, what are ordinary people in the ground doing?
But here's what's really going on in the heavens and connection with what they're doing.
Right. So we're going to pull back the veil, right?
So this is sort of the cosmic stuff that's going on, right?
While a huge priest is standing there sacrificing goats or a goat, right?
It's setting another one away, right?
But then sort of...
through this sort of cosmic atonement ritual, Azazel gets defeated and bound and punished,
and Yehoel sort of emerges victorious. So the idea here is that underlying the reality of
sacrifice is a kind of spiritual warfare. And this then gets into why this is associated with
Abraham, right?
You would know there's this sort of temporal problem of
like, well, wait a minute, the day of Atomina is an institute
until the minute is 16.
That's not only post like Exodus, that's post Sinai, right?
That's right.
Right.
Centuries from Abraham, right?
We're not gonna argue about how many.
But centuries from Abraham.
But so part of what happens, this is a form of argumentation
A form of argumentation in the kind of text that
are making arguments, but also just a way of narratively presenting things in narrative
tax of the second temple period. If you associate something with a figure from Genesis who sort
of precedes the Torah, you're presenting whatever you're presenting as being sort of more
ultimate than the Torah.
Yeah, I mean, and this feeds into, or I should say, draws on the sense that, I don't
almost every inch in culture has, which is that something that's before
for something else is greater.
And everything else is, you know, like the earlier thing,
later things are derived from it.
And so therefore, it has to be greater.
Right?
Like just like for instance, people will say that all philosophy
is just footnotes to Plato.
Right?
They'll say stuff like that.
The idea that Plato is the, you know,
the ultimate, the greatest philosopher, whatever.
Which is why then, you know, when Jesus talks about
the Messiah being David's Lord and yet
also his son, he, you know, he blows their minds by saying that because they're like, well,
if he's David's son, then isn't David greater, right?
Sort of a paradox, right?
Yeah, because because there's a standard way of thinking, which is that earlier things
are greater and everything else is, you know, comes later, it's lesser derivative, etc.
And that's why there's this fascination.
It's like a temple literature with the figure of Enoch.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
Because he sort of before all of this, he's before the flood even, right?
He's like, he's sort of the...
the first like truly or righteous man.
Yeah, so righteous that he ascends into heaven.
Yeah. And so whatever he sees, whatever he knew, whatever he had to teach
would be sort of more ultimate than anything that came later, more primordial, right, more
more of the deep wisdom, right, than the later things, right?
And so associating this with Abraham is a way of saying like,
This is sort of the
the really real reality that lies behind the ritual described in Leviticus.
Right. And you even find essentially, like this is essentially the argument that St. Paul
is doing, or a type of this argument that St. Paul is doing in Galatians and Romans,
when he sort of goes back before the Torah to Abraham to talk about faithfulness.
Yeah, yeah. And the promise is to Abraham. A greater, more ancient law.
Yeah, right like this.
and this is before, this is right.
And so what comes later,
doesn't sort of get rid of that, right?
It adds to that, right?
It brings more than that,
but it doesn't sort of void that or get rid of that.
Yeah, and so that's kind of the idea here behind,
even though, again, if you ask the question,
is this literally habit, right?
Like that is at work,
but that's what the text is trying to do.
So then the last part of the
apocalypse of Abraham is sort of the apocalypse proper in that this is where
Abraham sort of goes on this spiritual journey through the cosmos with
Yehovah as his guide, right, as the psychopath, which is sort of your typical
apocalyptic literature thing. Spiritual being is a guide, right, human is
taken up into the heavenly places. From that perspective, he sees all kinds of
Truths that underlie the events on earth in the past and the present.
future. Right. So interestingly, in terms of the identity of Yehoh-e again, when they
first ascend up into the heavens, they go sort of past the four living creatures, the
four cherubim, because that's what cherubim means is living creatures. Caravim means beasts,
Right. From Daniel and Ezekiel and Revelation for that matter.
even though Revelation hadn't been written yet,
when the Apocalypse of Abraham was.
Right, but we talked about how in Ezekiel,
those were the four main constellations
in Babylonian astrology.
So the idea is that was like the four quadrants
of the heavens were represented by those four creatures.
And so if God is enthroned on top of them,
he's above the sun, moon, and stars.
above the heavenly.
host, right? And when Abraham and Yeholl ascend up above them, Yeholl is like placed above them.
Yeah, which is another second power and heaven indication going on there.
Right. So that's another element there that points to that.
And so that puts you above it.
And so then.
The whole takes Abraham on this tour of the cosmos, and then after they've toured the
cosmos, Abraham finds out that, oh wait, that wasn't the actual cosmos.
That was the, that God had made, had created a prototype or blueprint or proof of concept
for the cosmos before he created the cosmos from it.
And your whole head actually taken Abraham out a tour of that model.
of the blueprint. So Abraham had been shown things the way they were supposed to be. Seems
to be the idea of the original. The way things were as God created them, not necessarily
the way they actually were or turned out. I mean, you can see where, although it doesn't
have to be this way, but you can see where Nostics like the Baga Males would be into this
idea. Like they would say, oh, we'll see that's that's sort of the real, the true.
cosmos and we just were down here, we're left in this kind of lesser.
Yeah, lame copy.
Not real. Yeah, yeah, exactly.
But it's that's not the last.
We have terminal play no brain, right?
Right.
This is shadow.
This is not real.
Um, yeah.
And so you could see how it could be interpreted that way, but it doesn't have to be interpreted
that way.
No, no.
Um, so, uh, and then, uh,
Abraham sort of gets after getting a tour of sort of physical cosmos or cosmos
in terms of space. He kind of gets a tour of time and history. So he sees
Adonyev being expelled from paradise. And the language and everything that's used, first of all,
very obviously intended to connect the expulsion of humanity from paradise to the exile
Yeah, to Babylon. Yeah. Yeah. And both of those events are characterized, are connected here and are characterized as being handed over to Azazal.
Yeah, because Azazal is that demon that's on the outside of the place where God dwells with his people. Right. Right.
Right, and sort of the rest of the world where God isn't is still under the power of his own.
The scary thing out in the woods.
Yeah.
The black go to the woods with a thousand young star that's that's
Schumnegrave
There's a little lovecraft I'm
Can't read that stuff
I don't know man having a having a creature called the black go to the woods with a thousand young
I mean that is pretty cool nicely creepy in it of it and you know and my literary hero J. R. Tolkien apparently was into or at least did read
it.
Lovecraft. Oh, it's very, it's very clear when you read that Lewis had to like when you read
the space trilogy. Oh, sure, sure, sure. I mean, the watch in the water is probably, you know,
on some level, I love crafty and beast. Yeah. But so and this connection, by the way,
is one of the between the exile and the expulsion for paradise is something you find
every
and second temple Jewish texts.
Yeah, yeah.
Like drawing those two things together.
So, but here it has that wrinkle.
And just being handed over to a Zazel
being expelled into the realm controlled by a Zazel,
here's another connection to the New Testament.
Think about how St. Paul, on two different occasions,
talks about somebody being excommunicated
from the churches being handed over to Satan.
Yeah, I mean, this is basically the idea of anathema,
which is look you have to stand outside
where it's cold and scary, and there's demons.
until you're ready to repent and come back.
Right. Right. And so, yeah, so you can see, again,
this is written after St. Paul lived.
This person isn't cribbing from St. Paul's,
St. Paul's not cribbing from them.
We're talking about just how did Jewish people think
in the first century about these?
Right. There's certain common motifs
in the way of thinking about it.
What is it thinking about these things?
And then, the talk of the way Abraham talks about cane
being possessed by his
He's the first person who that happens to put not the last.
Yeah, which I mean, this connects with that idea that in Genesis 4, that crouching at
your door thing where, you know, which is a demonic force, right?
That's going to take him over, you know?
Right.
And so, and when is a Zazel take somebody over, he uses that person to attack the righteous.
So King kills Abel, but all through history, there are these people under the control of
as well.
who try to attack God's people and destroy them, right, and attack the righteous and destroy them.
And this is related to what we saw in the earlier section, right. So you've got a Zazel,
there it is, Dragon for me, you got you, Ho-L there, but the actions going on in the world
are taking place. The sacrifice itself is being done by Abraham. Right. There's a human
who's doing the thing.
Right?
And the spiritual warfare is kind of happening.
around him. So the same kind of thing is happening with Cain,
except it goes the other way. Right. So it's depicting what happens
in Genesis 4 where God speaks to Cain, but then Sin is crouching in his
door, right, as as if right, much like with Abraham, there's God
there, right, you know, there's God there on the one side and a
a zeal on the other, right, and cane chooses to be possessed by a zeal.
and bring Azazel's works into the world by telling his brother.
Right?
So this section, as we're going through history,
sort of culminates in a description of the destruction of the Second Temple.
And this is why we're pretty sure it was after AD70 that this was written.
because right after it describes the
of the second temple, it goes on to describe the sort of 12 steps or 12 eras or 12 things
that unfold before the end of time, before the end of days, right? And those 12 things are like
super cryptic and mysterious, not like book of revelation or Daniel cryptic, like nosteridamas
script deck. Right.
open to massive different kinds of interpretations.
Yes.
Like wildly different, right?
And so someone could say, well, how do you know that the destruction of the Second Temple
wasn't also being predicted?
Well, it's described it very on the nose straight forward terms.
Right.
And it's the last thing described in those kind of terms before we get cryptic, which pretty
strongly implies that that was for the original writer of this.
That was history already.
Yeah.
That was the past already because of how he writes about it.
There's no vagaries at all about the destruction of the second temple.
But then as soon as you get past the destruction of the second temple,
everything gets really vague and weird and symbolic and, right,
very open to interpretation.
So it's pretty, pretty firm that this was written shortly after, right?
Uh...
by a non-Christian Jewish writer.
And then when you get to the end of the 12 things,
you start getting things.
They're still described symbolically and stuff,
but it's stuff we're more familiar with.
He has the idea of the final trumpet there,
which you also see in St. Paul, in Second Thessalonians.
And then after the final trumpet,
the Messiah comes and destroys his aisle
and destroys his enemies.
And then the last judgment happens in the resurrection.
Right, so we go back...
to sort of the familiar end of the world things within in first century Judaism and early Christianity
that we're used to at the end of that. And so there's just these 12 things in between there that
are weird and mysterious. Notice also though that so we had this image of Abraham doing this sacrifice
that brought about the defeat of a zeal, and now that same event is the Sc...
as not Yehoel, but the Messiah defeating Azazal,
and that happening at the end of the world.
Yeah, so there's a sense in which the sacrifice of Abraham,
as the day of atonement is kind of doing everything,
all of that self-effic stuff everywhere in history,
all at the same time.
Yeah, it's sort of this cosmic event more than any,
like claimed historical event,
and points to some kind of...
cosmic atonement that we're going to talk about so more than the second half.
So the last thing to really comment about in the text of the apocalypse of Abraham itself
before we move to that second half is within the cryptic parts,
there is this description, this cryptic description of A man who comes.
Okay, and that's all the description we're given of him is that he is A man.
No one stood up and interrupted it said what's his name?
So this is an amen and
so here's the description in
the cryptic part a man comes
some of the followers of a zeal and
People from the pagan nations and some of the sons of Abraham worship this man
Okay, but then some other sons of Abraham beat this man
Okay, and then after the man recovers from his beating
All those folks begin to worship him again
And when he sees this when Abraham sees this Abraham gets told by God through you whole that the man
Right is gonna be one of Abraham's descendants
That person is going to relieve the persecution of the Jewish people
And that he will be stood up on the last day and stood up there in this
Levanic maybe covering up a word for like resurrection, like rising, he raised
on the last day. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So if there's anything maybe that we might possibly think of as,
Oh, here's the Kristen bit.
This might be it. Maybe. Right cuz I kind of
It sounds like Jesus, right?
Right, right.
But it should be pointed out that nothing in there
isn't found in some way in the Old Testament already.
Well, yes, but also if this was coming from a Christian,
you wouldn't have him recovering from a beating.
You'd have him get killed.
Kill, yeah.
He'll come back to life.
Exactly, exactly.
Right, which we don't have.
So there's no death at resurrection here.
Until he's raised up on the last day.
Right. And what he does seems to be in relation primarily to the pagan nations.
Yeah, rather than to Israel. Not Israel itself. Right. And so what seems to be going on here
is that this is actually a reference to Jesus. That by the time it's being written,
And it's a historical reference to...
Jesus because we're about 50 years after the fact.
Yeah, and by this point, Jesus is very, very, very well known and the church is beginning
to expand considerably.
Right.
And so this is representing a non-Christian, Jewish perspective on nascent Gentile Christianity.
Yeah, so there's this sense of, okay, all these Gentiles are coming to worship Israel's
God.
Can we not be good for Jewish people?
Yeah, that's good.
That's good.
Fighting them some relief for persecution in this kind of thing.
Right.
That's good.
So how can we without saying, yeah, Jesus is our Messiah.
Without saying.
He goes from the dead without saying he's a Messiah.
Right.
So there's a really high someone who does it.
Isn't a Christian.
Yeah.
Sort of like these Christianity is beneficial.
face for him in our world and it turns out.
that there is actually a figure that was expected amongst some Jewish people.
There is a category for this that gets applied here.
So this is one of the earliest instances, I think, of the application of this category
to Jesus by a Jewish author.
That category being what's called the Messiah, Ben Joseph.
Yeah, and you call everybody that we, I can't remember which episode it was now,
but we talked in an earlier episode about there being
tradition of multiple, multiple Messiah's. We did an episode I think on just Messiah in general.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And I think we've even briefly talked about Messiah Ben Joseph in that as a
categorical. Right. And it's not just that there's multiple different versions of the Messiah.
There are traditions in which there are multiple Messiah's like there would be more than one.
And they'll do basically one, a kingly one, right. So sort of the one we usually think of as the Messiah
would be the Kingley Messiah, the Messiah Ben David, the son of David, right?
king and David's line, right? That's usually what we just say, the Jewish Messiah or the Messiah,
that's usually what we're talking about in our parlance. But there are pieces of Jewish tradition
about other Messiah figures. Messiah been Joseph. The son of Joseph is in Joseph in the book of Genesis.
As an Ephraim, the largest and central tribe of the northern kingdom of Israel,
Yeah, which is that got dispersed?
Right. And then closely associated then with the Gentiles.
Right. So then if you think about when we talked about the
testaments of the 12 patriarchs, previously in this series, we
talked about how in a couple of those testaments, it talks about
the, the northern tribes of Israel being reconstituted since
they were dispersed among the Gentiles like seed, they're
going to be reconstituted from the returning Gentiles coming
back to worship. People that are coming back to
worship Israel's God, the figure of the Messiah, Ben Joseph, the Messiah, the Son of Joseph,
the Son of Ephraim, is this figure who would come and gather, regather the North Kingdom
by gathering people from the nations to worship the God of Israel, to leave aside a
Dollar Tree, to leave aside other sinfulness and come to worship Israel's God.
and at various points throughout history.
Jewish writers, non-Christian Jewish writers, have to varying degrees
Recognize Jesus of Nazareth as this figure or as maybe being this figure or Christianity as a religion being this figure
For these various reasons so the apocalypse of Abraham
seems
to be at least so far the earliest testimony we have
And I don't know how much earlier you could get testimony than 8080, but to a non Christian
Jewish person sort of applying these traditions to Jesus of Nazareth to say that they don't
believe he's the Messiah been David, which of course we as Christians do.
Right.
Believe he's the Davidic Messiah.
But to say he is a Messiah in some sense and to recognize what's happening in Christianity
as a good thing and a movement of God.
That's not an artificial thing that rabbinic Judaism dreamed up centuries later to try to get
along better with Christians.
That is a tradition from very early on, right?
And applying that to Jesus starts to happen.
Places like here very early on.
Yeah.
There you are.
All right.
Well, that's basically our summary of the apocalypse of Abraham.
We're going to offer some comments, some more commentary on exactly everything that is going
on when we get back after the break.
First, we'll take a couple of questions right after this break.
So we'll see you in a second.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation
brought about a r-
reinterpretation of the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
But Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations,
Father Stephen D. Young surveyes Paul's life in writings,
interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's epistles,
liberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first-century Judaism, DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and help the reader reassess Saint Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
or Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
On this episode of Lord of Spirits Podcast,
we are talking about the apocalypse of Abraham,
one of the...
I just got an important communication from Amazon.
Oh, really?
They want me to organize my space with stylish bookcases.
Alright, I mean if you need to go do that.
Um, go ahead.
I don't know. I'll probably take too long.
I'm sure the heathen dogs would get in the way.
Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So if it all right, we are going to take a couple of questions.
Um, so waiting very patiently all the way from the great white
frigid north Ontario, we have a mirror.
So a mirror welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hello, fathers. Can you hear me? We hear you. Welcome. Awesome. Awesome. Yeah, so I have a question about are there any books that are dangerous to read because I was reading about St. Ignatius French and I'm hoping I'm saying that right, but he was talking about this one month on Mount Athos and he read the imitation of Christ. I can't remember which Catholic author but and the month became so delusional.
You'll just keep the pre-last you like chained up
or whatever, filling hot to the touch or whatever.
So I was wondering, like, can that happen?
Are there books where we should avoid something
or like that or anything?
Yeah.
I mean, and yeah, that was written by Thomas the campus,
by the way, from the 15th century.
I mean, I am certainly there have been times
in the history of the church where like books
have been destroyed, right?
particularly when you're talking during some of the imperial era of the Roman imperial era,
Byzantine Empire. But I don't recall, I mean, Father, correct me if I'm wrong about this,
but I don't recall conciliar decrees forbidding certain things from being read. Like, you must not
ever read this, and that is a rule for all Christians or something like that. I think…
well go ahead yeah go ahead you got to
contextualize
it a little right? Right. That's my thought is like is like the vast majority of Christians couldn't
read for most of his right right right but also it's like it wasn't an issue what yeah I mean I
think like if someone came to me I would say well what is it why do you want to read this book
you know are you are you doing research are you planning to submit yourself to the wisdom or
you know information whatever contained herein um because like the idea that reading Thomas
the campus is going to kind of magic.
destroy your spiritual life. I don't think that that's true. I mean, I don't know the particulars of this
this story about this Athonite monk, you know, and why he did that, what he was hoping to accomplish by that.
Obviously, it was not a good idea for him. Many people have read it and you know, didn't
you know, didn't fall into some kind of delusion or whatever. Although, I'm sure someone's
Someone's gonna write it and say actually every single person who...
was ever read it.
I don't think that's true.
So, I mean, I would say, you know, it's just like anything.
Like, on some level, all things are lawful,
but not all things are expedient.
You know, is it a good idea?
Is it worth your time?
Is this something that's actually gonna be valuable?
You know, I mean, mind you,
there are some kinds of literature
that are completely unredeemable.
Like, you know, you should not read pornography.
Not because there's a rule against it,
because it's terribly bad for you.
You know, like it's just,
we don't need a rule against it.
It's just, it's like, yes, there's a rule.
Do not drink poison.
That's a rule.
Like no, you just shouldn't drink poison
because it's not a kill yet.
You know, I guess I'm not aware
of like officially forbidden books.
Well, I don't know.
Yeah, so for the most part, right?
99%
of the time, this is a very personalized question that really should be between a person and their
spiritual father. Right. Right. It's not it. Is this a book that should be read? Is this a book
I should be reading right now? Yeah. Right. And that's going to be different for different people.
Right. Like I famously for decades now, because I'm an old man, have read Nietzsche every
and that's not like a
I recommend to people. Right. There's a lot of people who don't need to be reading
Nietzsche. Where it's either a waste of time or might be deleterious to them in some way.
Right. So that's not right. My conscience has been seared as by a hot iron.
So there's no damage, further damage possible to my soul.
But, so 99% of the time it has to do with the person, right?
And that's I'm also leaving in the has to do with the person category books that are just frivolous.
Right, because as we talked about with the whole clean and unclean thing, the opposite of holy is common, not evil. Right.
And so like reading novels that are just dumb entertainment
because you need a break and you need relaxation is a huge
with human physical and mental limitations, right?
Like reading Charles Dickens, which is the literary equivalent of a sitcom.
Come on.
It absolutely is massive shade.
Charles Dickens would be writing sitcoms if he was alive today.
They were serialized to chapter at a time in newspapers.
Just every sitcom has done an adaptation of a Christmas Carol.
It's just an indication of how far we've fallen.
QED.
Anyway.
Hahaha.
Right. But just reading because you know, that's fine. Right. Like I'm not saying there's
something wrong with that. Now, even that you need to discuss with your spiritual father
because there's an issue of, you know, how much of your time are you spending doing that?
Right. If you have a job that's mentally taxing and you want to come home for an hour
and read some, you know, John Grisham novel or, you know, Stephen King novel or something,
Right, just to unwind at the end of the day, that might be
totally spiritually healthy and fine for you. Right? There are other people who become obsessive
about all kinds of things and who that might not be good or they might be, you know, squirreling away,
you know, way too much time that they should be using on other things, doing that, right?
There are actually in the world evil books. There are, there are literal evil books.
You will probably...
probably not run into them. You won't just run into them walking around.
This is going to come off as kind of a tease, but I'm not going to go further into the
story. But just through a long series of events, I was mailed a copy of a 18th century German
literal magical text. Wow.
Actually, the dispose of it, to dispose of it. And literally an hour of it sitting in my
email book box warped and rotted out the wood of my mailbox.
How about that? Yeah, I burned it for the record. So there are actual evil books out there that no one should read and no one should even know. Right. But unless you're going out looking for like a cult books.
books. And by occult books, I don't mean the ones you find in the like astrology occult
section that parts of noble that are about crystal power and stuff. Those are just dumb.
We'll lose like a few points.
reading them but like they're not going to bring demons into your home right there are actually
I'm talking about actual evil books you'd have to go out and find them on purpose for the most
yeah um and don't right like that seems obvious um but those books are and have been these are
the kind of books that like in the book of acts when they say they're coming out and burning
their books of sorcery and stuff. Right.
Those are the kind of books I'm talking about
Yeah, right. That's not touches a dragon's books. That's not right rock albums, right?
This is a whole other thing and when you're around it, you know it
so
But that's you know this fraction of a percent of books in the world right right
Well does that help you Amir?
That does if I can just add one comment if that's okay sure
Yeah.
So one thing about this question, I know it's a fake book, but the one book like the Necronomicon or whatever.
I can remember who it's by, but that just reminds me of it saying, oh, if I read this, I'm going to go crazy or whatever, you know.
But yeah, that's a fictional book though.
Yeah, exactly.
Now, my wife has a cookbook based on it called the Necronom-nom-nomicon.
Of course she does.
all right. Thanks for calling
a mirror. We're going to take one
more call and we have Gregory
calling from at least his phone
says he's from Jacksonville, Florida.
Although are you from Jacksonville?
I am now from Jack. You are.
I wasn't in Colorado. You were
from Colorado. Actually now that
I look closely at the call
board, your phone does say you're
from Colorado, but you say that
you're from Jacksonville and we
believe you've gone from the heights
to the depths. Oh boy.
It's true.
from my question. I have a question about dragons. Okay. You've come to the right place.
From the heights, you said then the word cherub is translatable to living creature. And I
know that Sarah can meet serpent or like fiery. And I guess it just occurred to me. I
queued into the idea that I've been always interested in St. George, the dragon slayer.
And I'm of firm belief that what he bought was maybe not carbon-based.
but it was definitely a dragon, like unquestionably a dragon.
So I'm wondering if maybe you can bring some clarification
to the idea of like the falling of angels
and the falling of fire angels being capable of being
in a sense living, but also maybe not necessarily
carbon-based, but still we can interact with them
and St. George can slay one.
And so I just want to see the, if you have anything
that maybe you can share with me about that relationship.
Yeah, I mean, there's like dragons. I mean, there's good dragons and bad dragons, you know,
I mean, generally speaking, particularly in Western Christian tradition, most dragons are
bad, although not all, but you know, and in the Orthodox tradition, yeah, there's bad
dragons, right, the serpent, the devil, you know, all this kind of stuff, but they're
are also good dragons, which are the obedience set of them. And you can even see...
Like I was actually at a I was actually at a Greek monastery in California this past weekend and on
their iconostasis they had both good and bad dragons. So you could tell the good ones because they
were up on top of the iconostasis like right next to the cross, you know kind of honoring the
cross and guarding the cross. So these were functioning like setterfim. But then on among other
images on the the Holy Doors, these incredible beautiful carved wood Holy Doors, you see dragons that
that are being scared away.
angels with swords. So clearly those are not good dragons because they're being attacked by angels.
So St. George is obviously functioning in that same way. He's functioning this kind of
mechaelic way, like St. Michael, the dragon slayer, the original dragon slayer in a lot of ways
as he's depicted in the book of Revelation and stuff. So I mean, Father, I mean, comment on this idea
of living creatures.
How does that, like I tend to think that for instance, the reason that Western dragons
have four feet is because of this kind of almost a half merger of set up him with cherubim,
you know, because cherubim usually depicts those four footed, but set up him either no
feet or maybe just, well, yeah.
So it's also worth mentioning that according to the cynic sorry of his feast, St. Michael
is also a serif.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So maybe dragon on dragon action.
Um.
But yeah, so what's really meant by Caravim is like a lamasu, actually the original context.
So think, you know, it gets translated Zoey, like living creature in Greek and then the
faces, the four faces are described, right?
But the idea is more of like a finks like creature from our perspective, right?
we think of what we think of as
or Alamisu, which is the Babylonian version that has like a human head and then like a lion body and wings.
So it's more a sort of typicaletherium or thing than a dragon thing.
And so like in for Babylonians those were different because the dragons were sort of the primordial.
God's, whereas the Lamasu, which would correspond more to the cherubim, were sort of the
guardians, the throne guardians of the gods, right? So there sort of, there was a definite
rank system there. They get merged a little more. So what you really have happening in
And the Hebrew Bible is that the Hebrew Bible is constantly interacting with neighboring
traditions.
And those traditions are not identical.
So for example, a lot of the Hebrew Bible is interacting at the same time with Mesopotamian
traditions and Egyptian traditions.
And then also Khenaic traditions, in addition.
So when you think about...
Egyptian traditions and the way serpents function in Egyptian tradition, it's much closer to the way that the Lamasu, the Kerovim, function in Mesopotamian traditions,
whereas the dragons are sort of elevated above that in Mesopotamian tradition.
And so I think that's why you get the places
in the Hebrew Bible where you get this kind of equivalence and semi-merger between
Seraphim and Cherubim is because these different roles in Egyptian versus Mesopotamia tradition
and the Hebrew Bible interacting with both of those at the same time.
If that makes sense.
It doesn't take either of those as being 100% accurate.
Does it like pick one and say, okay, this is the one that's true?
Both of those sets of pagan traditions aren't actually true.
It's interacting with and trying to refine both of them.
And so you get a little loss of clarity between those two sets of beings.
Does that help clear things up for you, Gregory?
There's a million follow-ups, but I'll try my best to retain those for like maybe email chain or something for the Facebook group.
Okay, Doc.
I guess mainly it was...
It was mainly just the idea of, I guess,
Charibund Sarra from Remension is being the highest ranks among angels before their fall.
And then after their fall, you would assume that they still sort of hang onto this title as like biggest brute, you know?
And the idea of the spiritual world and the physical world just being the world.
Like, there is no one, and then the other, there's just there is, right?
And it's mostly the idea of what Saint George accomplished to me is more than just like, oh,
it kicked a D-
been out by praying and it's a little bit more violent like physical and physical I guess
I'm just making sure I'm not like in a really bad wrong thinking with that.
But it's also not like you killed one of the last surviving dinosaurs.
Right.
Right. That kind of total materialists
kind of way of going about it from a young earth perspective.
Right.
of light. Oh, just some random dinosaur had survived in Libya.
and St. George killed it.
I mean, it should be mentioned, right?
Like, St. George accumulates lots and lots of different elements to his story.
But the one that's always the most important is that he's a martyr, right?
And to me, that's, you know, there's so much, so much in our hymns about the martyrs
defeating demons by virtue of being martyred.
I think that that's the key to interpreting what's going on there.
That doesn't mean that we shouldn't tell the story in the way that it's traditionally
told.
We absolutely should.
Absolutely should.
But I think it's important, as Father Stephen alluded to, to not make it about, oh,
he was just this amazing soldier who killed a big lizard, a demon lizard, but a lizard.
Um.
But yeah, yeah, there's a golden mean. Yeah, exactly.
Between these two extremes of just spiritualizing everything or just trying to turn everything into a modernist materialist kind of thing.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. All right. Thank you very much for calling.
Okie doke, where are we going now father?
When we talk some more atonement stuff I think, I mean it's interesting that we did that
episode on atonement a-
a while ago now, a few years ago now,
and it's still one of the ones I think that a lot of people
come back to and a lot of people have questions about
and are really fired up about.
So, I mean, this text offers us the opportunity
to go deeper and some other way.
Yeah, in touch on some of that.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, so as we said, we've got a depiction in this text.
Again, from at least some quantity, some element
of the Judaism's of the second-templar period.
who are, as we see in this text, looking for a kind of cosmic day of atonement to happen.
Right? A kind of cosmic atonement to happen.
And so what we want to do for the rest of this half is,
kind of talking about, well, why would they be looking for that?
And what would the shape of that cosmic atonement that they were looking for be?
Right?
and spoilers in the third half.
we're going to be talking about Christ's atonement and how that relates to this expectation,
this Jewish expectation of a cosmic atonement, right? How those things intersect,
right? The actual fulfillment of it in Christ, how that intersects with the Jewish expectation.
So when we talk about kind of this cosmic day of atonement, we're looking for,
We're talking about a fulfilled day of a tone.
So this is not something completely different than the day of atonement in Leviticus 16.
It is not just like, well that thing stinks or it's dumb, so we're going to get rid of it,
we're going to replace it with something else.
That's not what they're looking for.
No, that's not what fulfillment means.
This is fulfilled in the sense of filled full, like we've talked about before.
So this is the final form.
Right.
Yeah.
Taking the structure, taking the structure, the meaning, the effect, the power of the
of the day of atonement and filling that up, right? The ultimate example, right? The ultimate
instance of it, right? That's what we're talking about. And so that's why we've been describing
it as cosmic. This is not cosmic like it has to do with space, right? Silver surfer does
not make it appearance. This is cosmic in the sense of it has to do with the whole cosmos,
Right, the whole creation.
This is going to affect the whole creation.
And there are several reasons why people of the Second Temple period,
especially in the first century BC, the first century AD,
with this text is written, why they're looking for that kind of thing.
Right? And one big one is that Yom Kapoor, the day of atonement,
the ritual that they've been doing since it was given in Leviticus 16,
kind of points to
its own limits. Yeah, yeah, it's just limited by nature. And you can tell that. Right.
By the practice of it, right, practicing it is going to show you the limitations. Right.
So for example, we have to do it every year. Yeah, which suggests that it kind of wears
off or is needed again, you know. Meaning it's not it's limited in its effectiveness.
it's limited in the duration of its effectiveness, at least, right?
Yeah.
That we have to keep doing this.
It's additional to the other sin offerings and peace offerings.
So we've got this daily and weekly cycle of sin offerings and peace offerings
going on to deal with sin.
And then we also need to do the day of atonement once a year, right?
So clearly the day of Atomit by itself is somewhat limited.
in terms of how it's able to deal with sin, which is the very problem it's there to deal with.
Now, that said, we have to be careful. This is, again, a point that St. Paul always makes very
carefully when he's talking about the fulfillment of things of the Torah, that this is not to say,
Yom Kippur was bad, the name of the tome was bad, that it didn't work, it did everything it was
supposed to do, then everything Leviticus 16 said it would do. Right? The problem is
not with the day of atonement, the problem is not with the Torah, the problem is with humans,
the humans who are trying to practice it and failing. Right? So the reason you have to do it every
year, and the reason you have to do all these other sin offerings and this is human sinfulness.
Right? The real problem is that the humans keep sinning. Yeah. The people of the camp keep sinning.
the Israelites keep sitting.
And making this this perpetual thing that has to be...
That has to be dealt with right and
Remember what we're talking about when we talk about the Israelites keep sinning
Because a lot of us were brought up in a in a Western Christian context. We're lack of a better term
Where we look at sinning as oh making bad choices
Doing bad things. Well people just keep doing bad things. They just knock it off right
That would make confession really.
really easy for me if I could just, you know, people come and tell me what they did. I can
just go, well, knock it off. Stop sitting. Yeah. Just quit it. I'm not preaching sermons
like that, but. Stop it. Come on, man. Yeah. We all know that's not how it works, right?
That sin is this power, right, that has a hold of people like it's described in the apocalypse
of Abraham.
Now that's getting...
that from from the Hebrew Scriptures, right? That sin is something that takes a hold of you.
And once it's got a hold of you, you can't just stop.
Yeah, right? You can't just quit, right? You're not free to do that anymore.
When sin has you in its grip. And so every year, the day of Atomin is dealing with the sins that
that people have committed, which are like symptoms of the
disease, right? And it's dealing with the effects and the stain and the taint, right,
of of the sin, but the people remain infected with the sin itself. So it would be like if
you had a horrible disease and we treated your symptoms so that you could function. And
Once a year we cleaned out your whole house.
burned all your bedding and clothes and gave you new so that you wouldn't spread the disease.
Right. But never actually tried to cure your disease. Because maybe we couldn't.
Right. And so we had to just keep treating it and treating it and treating it. That wouldn't
mean there was a problem with the treatments. That means there's a problem with this disease.
Right. So we see that limit there.
But then complicating that even further.
And this is something that doesn't weigh on us, right?
In the way that it weighed on the Jewish people of the first century BC,
the first century AD is it's not just that this was true,
but also they were still living under the consequences of that sin.
and the failure of their fathers to correctly manage that,
sinfulness with the Torah.
So the northern kingdom, most of the tribes of Israel, most of the people of Israel had been
destroyed and were just gone. They had been wiped out by the Assyrians. And those who were left,
right, the Judeans were the descendants of the tribe of Judah and a few from Benjamin and some
Levites, right? They had all been exiled in Babylon.
And while some of them had taken the opportunity to go back to Judea, a lot of them hadn't.
And when they got back to Judea, it wasn't the same.
Right?
I mean, they built a new temple, but the glory of God sort of didn't show up.
Yeah, they all kind of noticed that.
the Hasimony is managed to get into
Independence for Judea briefly, but it was briefly.
Then they were under the Romans, which is worse than the Greeks in a lot of ways.
Right. And so that exile wasn't really over.
The Jewish people who were left were scattered all over the world.
The ones in Palestine were not doing well under the Romans.
Thanks, I'll hand truly in.
And so this is something and now, you know, at the time the apocalypse of Abraham was
gay, the second temple has been destroyed by the Romans.
So the Romans are trying deliberately trying to de-judge the whole region, right?
Just building a third temple and purifying the sanctuary with goat blood was not going
to solve all this.
Yeah, it was just a
temporary measure to clean things up.
Right.
That wasn't going to fix everything.
Because building the second temple and purifying it with blood had not fixed everything.
So it's not just we have this disease and the day of atonement is treating it but not
curing it.
And he actually deteriorated from this disease to a point that's near terminal.
And because that treatment can't cure the disease, it also can't restore us to health and bring us back to life.
Right.
So I see how this isn't going to do it.
And so from that perspective, they then envision, okay, well, what would do it?
Yeah, yeah what version of this form we have this form this shape this outline this pattern
in the day of atonement.
What version of that, what form of that could solve the problem?
Could restore a style, could sure us, could do the job.
And that's where the images that we get, for example, in the apocalypse of Abraham and another second-devil Jewish writings of this cosmic atonement.
Frankly, the picture we get, we're talking about this one and the third half of the picture we get in the New Testament, right of the atonement.
Right.
That's where this comes in.
Right. So we need to have a purification, but it needs to be a final purification. Right.
Right. Well, it doesn't need to be repeated. It needs to be dealt with once and for all.
Yeah. I mean, I think like, especially if you think about where the Jews are at this point in their
history, you know, I mean, as you said, they weren't the Greek, they weren't the Romans. This is
is not great, but there's no clear, there's no set, there's no way, there's no way that
things are going to be like they were under David.
That's without God directly intervening.
Yeah, exactly.
Like, the world is encroaching in on them.
Empires have taken an interest in them
and have taken their spot over and over again.
You know, like, it's, and they cannot keep them at bay.
They do not have the power for that.
Right.
So this idea of this final hope, it's only makes sense
that there's going to be this desire there.
Right. Right. And so yeah, and even just them starting to now practice the Torah, again,
wouldn't cut it without God directly intervening. Right. So the fairsake position at this time
was not, oh, if we all just start following the Torah perfectly, we'll all be fine. No.
The fairsake position was if we begin to follow the Torah and show our faithfulness to God,
in contrast to our previous unfaithfulness.
Then God will intervene
Yeah, yeah, right that will bring about God's intervention. So
This isn't like oh well the Pharisees thought just Torah keeping was the solution to everything and
You know then there were these other disigant groups who thought God was gonna apocalypticly intervene
No, this is this is across the board the question is
How will God intervene?
Can we do something to bring about God intervening?
How will he intervene?
Those are the discussions.
Yeah, I mean, and this is one of the things
I think that underlines if you actually read the Torah.
Like, like there's this,
especially this dispensationalist idea
that the Torah is kind of, you know,
track A for salvation and then Jesus.
It's a means of personal salvation, yes.
Yeah, like, like, did you read it though?
Does it say that ever anywhere in it?
Like that these commandments are gonna result in this.
Doesn't say that.
It's just not in there.
Yeah.
You know?
So yeah.
So the Pharisees like this, the only people who thought God wasn't going to intervene directly
were the Sadducees.
And that's why they became Roman collaborators.
Right.
Because like this is why they got rich on this earth because they're like, there's nothing
else coming.
We need to just do what we need to do here.
Yeah.
Right.
It's kind of nihilistic being a sadgercy.
That's why they don't exist anymore.
They got what they wanted.
Anyway, or as someone once said, they have their reward.
Right.
So there has to be this final intervention by God.
And in terms of that final intervention,
that final atonement,
that has to be a purification,
not just of a sanctuary or of a camp or of a nation,
but of the whole cosmos,
the whole universe.
whole creation has to be purified. Right? Meaning, and what that means is the
things that are done in the day of Atonement have to be done finally and
completely. So the devil, a zeal, whatever we want to call him, right? And all
the powers of evil, right? The deviled powers have to be dealt with in a final
Right, bound and prisoned, punished.
done. Sin as a power in the world. Right? Sin came into the world through Adam. St. Paul summarizes
for us at Romans 5. Right? Through one man, sin came into the world. Sin needs to be removed from
the world. That power of sin, that thing that was stalking Kane, needs to be shoved back in its box
which is the same box as Hazel the devil and his ill can eat are going to be imprisoned.
Right. That needs to go away.
Because then human beings will be free freedom is not being able to do what you want
Freedom is being able to flourish
Yeah
Yep, yep
Freedom is free the freedom to destroy yourself is not freedom
Yeah, the freedom to sin is not actual freedom that's slavery. Yeah, I mean it's like I
I
I recently gave a sermon in which I was talking about how slavery to sin is described as debt
in some places in the New Testament and that continuing to sin even after you've been
forgiven is like paying a debt that you don't have to pay.
You keep paying it as though you're still enslaved to that creditor, but you're not.
You can you're free. You don't have to do it anymore. You can laugh. You can laugh. So
All right. Well, that's the second half. Yeah. I'm sorry. Go ahead. Go ahead.
Follow. I was just going to say so now third half we're going to talk about. Okay. This is the shape
of the expectation and a little bit of why they had it. Yep. Right. And now we're going to talk
in the third half about with that in mind, let's look at Christ's atonement. Yes, indeed. All right.
We're gonna take our second final break and we'll be right back with this episode.
of Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
This March join us for the 31 books of March sale event
at Ancient Faith Store in celebration of the...
events 10th anniversary were offering a large selection of books at 50% off every day
from March 1 through March 31. Over 150 titles we set each morning at 9 a.m. Central.
Explore books on Orthodox faith, theology, history and more. All at a discounted price.
You'll also find children's books and titles by popular podcasters and posts from ancient
faith video. Each day brings a fresh collection of books at an incredible
visit us at door.enginefaith.com.
There's not a day you'll want to miss
during 31 books of March.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now
at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back.
Back when she's a big famous commercial lady used to slum it with us.
Yes, that's right. I told people it's that was the voice of Trudy. We just heard some people don't and let's
They've ever called they may not know what Trudy actually sounds like.
Or or right think about this maybe if you hang around with us too long either of us you end up just
Becoming a disembodied voice. Is that what happened to Steve?
I think maybe and now it happened to I feel a little bit bad
because sometimes when people meet Steve, they will,
and they hear him talk, they're like,
you're the voice of Steve, he's like, I'm a person.
So guys, if you meet Steve, don't call him that.
Don't call him that.
I mean, we all saw what this kind of invisible joke
did to John Cena, he finally snapped.
So I'm expecting a Steve Christophero heel turn,
like any day now, he's just gonna start
washing out at random children.
Who are fans of his work?
It's just a TV show
Yeah, I also want to say so so I mentioned the beginning you know everybody get your tickets for
Lord of Spirits Fest in October
I also just want to throw out especially for those listening live
My final speaking engagement for this lens is happening this weekend. I'm gonna be at scene John the Baptist
Antiochian Orthodox Church in Po-
boost falls Idaho this weekend. We're doing a retreat all day long and it's free. So people
up there in Eastern Washington, Western Northern Panhandle of Idaho, which actually by the
way apparently father includes our YouTube guy Simon. Simon told me he's gonna come to
retreat. So everybody if you come to retreat, you can meet ancient faith celebrity Simon
Nelson, the U.K. showing you his drawings.
So bring your YouTube's and you can have Simon sign them
right there at the retreat.
I mean, that's pretty great way up there in Northern Idaho.
So again, masterful self-shield.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
So what's in the third half, Father?
Is this really, isn't this really all just about
penal substitutionary atonement?
Well, we're going to do a PS.
say about PSA. Nice. I mean, it's low hanging fruit, but thank you. It is. Yeah.
We didn't get any calls yet. I'm kind of surprised. We need to. I turn them all off.
We will. I've had it with people. Let's start talking about
people's substitutions. You're a total. Yeah. So, I'd like to think that us talking about
addressing paedal substitutes rate.
at this point would be beating a dead horse, but this horse is very alive. Oh, totally.
Yes. And kicking, right? Yeah. Like, despite the best efforts of a growing number of people,
even within Protestantism now, to point out that that dog don't hunt.
But this is going to be less, as may have happened in certain previous episodes,
episodes, Father Andrew and I using PSA as a pinata and more by way of clarification.
Those would be a little bit of hitting it with a stick. I mean, that's pretty fun.
Yes. And ironic. What do you think about it? But, um,
But, um...
So...
But what are the first...
the first things we could say in the context of what we're talking about in this episode is
the kind of cosmic atonement we were just talking about
that comes out of the Hebrew scriptures and this expectation and this need felt by Jewish people
of the first century BC, for century AD.
Penal substitution and Penal substitution atonement
doesn't do a cosmic atonement like that.
It's fun to make
doesn't answer the needs, those needs, right? Right?
You can say, well, okay, the New Testament just completely redefines atonement and blows
all their expectations out of the water. Maybe, except for the fact that
penal substitution atonement is less full than what they were expecting, not more.
Yeah, the expectation is for a cosmic cleanup.
not. Right. Not that's not what
people substitution
does. In fact, an individual debt fix.
Right.
Petyl substitution does nothing about the cosmos or creation.
Right. Because it's at all.
Yeah.
Right.
Petyl substitution is completely individualistic.
Yeah. Like where's Israel in all of that?
Like it's not even in the picture even.
Community of Israel, all that's totally out of the picture.
It's just a question of what Christ the Tobit has thought to do in the
Okay.
of certain individuals, not even all individuals, usually, right? Certain individuals.
But as nothing to do with creation, nothing to do with sin is a power. It's just a
question of sins and punishment, right? So that said, so it sort of fails that test, right? So
So people will say, what I mean by this is
people will make this argument sometimes.
And I don't think it's an accurate argument.
I think if you study who the Messiah was
in Jewish expectation, I don't think the argument
I'm about to make holds water.
The dog doesn't hunt.
Yeah.
But you will hear people say
who haven't really studied it.
And if you wanna study it,
you can start by listening to our episode on Messiahship.
But they'll say, well, okay,
there was this expect
at the time of Jesus of this kind of political Messiah,
Allah, John, her canister, one of the Hasmonians,
right, one of the Macabeeed rulers
who would come in and overthrow the Romans.
And but Jesus comes as the actual Messiah
and he blows that out of the way,
he does so much more than that, right?
So even though I don't think that's correct
about Jewish expectation, the argument itself
at least kind of make sense.
because you have a small expectation,
oh, this person is gonna set up a political kingdom
on Earth over a particular strip of land, right?
Versus what Christ actually did,
which is so much bigger than that, right?
But here with a tonement,
the expectation was for this cosmic thing
that would radically transform the entire creation.
Purifying it from sin and evil,
dealing with the demonic powers once and for all, right?
all of these things.
things, and instead we got, well, okay, God isn't going to punish you individual person
for the individual sins you have committed. That's far more narrow and small and finite
than the expectation. Yeah. That's the opposite of fulfillment. That's a denuded kind of thing.
But we also, we need to write one of the things that I feel
we haven't done adequately when we've talked, when we've critiqued Piedel substitution before,
is clarify exactly what it is because almost every discussion I enter into about this with anyone,
including Orthodox people, shows me that most people have no idea what it is.
Right. And so they'll either say like it seems right to me or I would say based on, and what they're
actually talking about isn't what Piedel's
Amstitutia is doing in a total of minutes.
So we want to kind of hear.
Who originally defines that? Is that like, is that a John Calvin thing? Is that?
I mean, who's who's laying that? It comes out of the Calvinist strand of reform tradition.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Now, previous to that and what still holds in the Roman Catholic Church,
give or take, I mean, there's a really real problem of
of pointing at anything and defining what actual
Roman Catholic doctrine is now.
as exemplified by the fact that anytime we or anyone else not Roman Catholic tries to do it,
we're always told we're wrong. Could you have you considered you might just always be wrong,
Father? Yeah, well, it's impossible. It is impossible for an non-Roman Catholic to correctly even
define not like they might have a valid argument against it, but even define what it is, even describe
what it is you can't do. It is, I mean, it's, it is a moving target especially, especially,
What's the rest of your...
last like 150 years. It's just right. Because if I quote the council of Trent, somebody
will point at something else. If I quote the catacombs over the Catholic church, oh,
well, that's not authoritative. That's just suggested. If I'd guys, right, you can go on
and on forever. Right. But anyway, if you want to play that game at any time I have actually
just nailed it beyond reproach, I just get called mean. Right. So I'm not even bothering
anymore. I mean, you are mean. But yes, I'm a mean man. Cool and vicious at my court.
a wonderful community of people around me and my parish, but they're the best. And you
are an overlord who is. You are there.
There are sins Lord, I get over them every Sunday. Yeah. Um, but okay. But yeah. So like
is it related to I mean, there is a medieval right? And that's what I do. I do have a Catholicism
satis back at least. Yeah. You know, to some extent, at least they've never rejected
and Somov-Catterberry who they consider a state, right?
And Kurt A. Somov.
So satisfaction theory is what prevailed for many centuries at least.
Yeah, I mean, it's within Roman Catholicism.
And it's baked into it's baked into it's baked into the whole purgatory model too, right?
Which is right.
Your sins can be forgiven, but you still have to author
offer satisfaction to God for those sins.
So you're going to kind of toast for a while.
And then you well, that's it.
Wait, now to see you're going down too far into the, that we've got explained
temporal guilt and stuff.
So I know, I know, I know.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah.
You don't want to go that far now, the Ramitrile, but-
Leave that for another day, but it is-
Right, right.
The idea of satisfaction theory is,
there's a problem between God and humans, right?
And that's humans sinning, right?
And humans sinning is an affront to God
whom they're sinning against, right?
And that situation needs to be made right, right?
There needs to be justice.
The situation has to be resolved somehow.
and in
And the idea of satisfaction is that Christ offers himself as a sacrifice to the Father.
The Father is pleased with that sacrifice.
And so because he is pleased with the sacrifice that Christ offers him, right,
he accepts that sacrifice and things are made right between God and man.
All right, his deep redustus is satisfied.
by the sacrifice of Christ. And then the benefits of that are given to individual human persons
in a variety of ways we won't go down all those rabbit trails. Sure, sure. We're talking about this show.
Right. But there is no element here of, as the penal and penal substitution, of God punishing Christ
particular sins.
Yeah, you know, you flipped off your brother the other day and so Jesus has to experience this.
We've just got a window into Father Andrew's home life by the example that immediately sprang
to mind.
I don't think I've seen my kids flipping each other's a bird.
They're not saying they're always nice to each other.
just you were thinking about Clyde anyway okay so
Yeah, so that's a different thing than Petyl substitute sherry atonement.
The Roman Catholic Church has never traditionally believed in Petyl substitute sherry atonement.
In fact, built into, you read Roman Catholic doctoral expressions about this, they talk about
how one drop of Christ's blood, him offering one drop of his blood, would have been sufficient
as a sacrifice to make a tonement for the whole world.
right, because he's offering it as a pleasing sacrifice to God. So there's no kind of idea.
This is within a better understanding, right? I don't think it's perfect because it's a little different than the Orthodox view, but a better,
still a better in the 11th century understanding of sacrifice, for example, then what you find later, especially in Protestant circles.
So that's not penal substitution.
Penal substitution comes about within the reform tradition because it has to.
Okay, it has to. You can't really hold to Penal substitution and not be a Calvinist. It doesn't work.
Because what Penal substitution says is that there is a punishment for the particular sins committed by
particular people.
Yeah, I get to crime and punishment idea and Christ in the past
Took the punishment for particular sins
committed by particular people
And therefore those people are not punished for those sins
Meaning you have to accept that L in tulip limited atonement to really believe in penal substitution
Thank you.
Now, you could be a universalist.
As we pointed out before, when we talked about universalism on the show, someone like David
Bentley Hart is basically a liberal Calvinist.
It's like a Barney and Calvinist.
It's all just modern.
Bart was reformed.
He's a Calvinist who says just basically everybody's elect.
Right?
You just say every human is elect.
Or you have to say some subset of humans.
Thank you.
But it does not make sense for anyone to say Christ took the punishment for sins XYZ committed by person A
But they didn't accept Jesus and so now God is going to also punish them for those same sins
Right, that doesn't make sense
So if you're gonna believe in people substitute your atonement you have to be some kind of Calvinist
The original Armenians
not Armenians.
Armenians.
There are Armenian Armenians.
They probably can be wearing our money.
And there's an Armenian comedian.
But the original Armenians believed,
did not believe that Christ,
well, I shouldn't say the original Armenians,
the original remonstrant Armenians did.
But that's not who we think of as our mini-
who we think of as Armenians are Wesley in Armenians.
And the Wesley in Armenians, Wesley did not say, right,
that Christ died for everyone's sins in a penal substitution way.
The distinction between him and a Calvinist was the Calvinist said,
God chose according to his will,
according to his good pleasure, whose sins Christ would die for.
Whereas the Armenian, the Wesleyan Armenian,
said God knew in advance who would accept Christ and so Christ died only for those sins but either way
you got the limited atonement part. Yeah yeah yeah. Right so that isn't getting you out of that.
Right. Wesley and Arminians are sort of like three point maybe four point Calvinists honestly.
So that...
That's what we're talking about. We're talking about PSA. Just don't
extend right now that is not orthodox. The orthodox church does not nor has it ever
taught penal substitute area tone. Okay. Despite what you may have heard from some
catacumins slash inquirer online or self-appointed teacher online.
right. Uh, despite what you may
heard from some very well-meaning priests and monks and maybe even some bishops
somewhere. Okay. Well, why would they say things like that? Well, I'm not talking
about cranks on the internet, right? Who could explain their wacky behavior?
I'm talking about the the well-meaning priests and monks and maybe even bishops
somewhere. Yeah, what's going on there? Why are they saying that? It's yeah, it's
It's because there are certain kind of shorthands.
that are being used to define penal substitute near atonement that aren't actually what it really is.
Right. Right.
Transcendence.
And this is on both sides.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right. This is on both sides.
In the sense that this isn't just these well-meaning orthodox people.
There's a lot of Protestants who would say that they do believe in penal substitute
you don't actually understand what it is.
Right, or who and you explain.
to him what it is they're like, oh no, I don't believe that. Right. So just saying Christ
died for our sins, that is not penal substitutionary atonement.
Sure.
Necessarily. Yeah. Okay. That's open to a wide variety of interpretations of in what
sense Christ died for our sins. Yeah. Even saying Christ died in our place in some way is
not necessarily penal substitution.
Yeah, I mean, it's sort of substance.
Tutionary on some level, but right or on our behalf
Right
That's yeah, which is actually closer to what the Greeks says of those passages. He died on our behalf
He died with benefit to us. That's not penal substitution
So here's the core
Here's the very core of this and why the Orthodox Church has never accepted it
Okay, and this is very clear the teaching of Calvin and the Calvinist tradition
You
We've talked before on the show about how, say, John of Damascus distinguishes between
two kinds of death, and this is a basic theological distinction in Orthodox theology.
He isn't saying this to innovate.
He's saying this in his expositing on theology and summarizing the theology of the fathers
before him.
So this is, he considers this basic Christian theology that there's two kinds of death.
is used in the scriptures in our tradition in two.
different senses. One of them is physical death. Physical death is when the human soul is separated
from the human body. The other way it is used is to refer to spiritual death. When the human soul
is separated from God, which is the source of life, and that's why it can be called death.
For humans, right?
When God says to Adam, on the day you eat of the tree you will surely die,
he's talking about spiritual death and that happens to Adam on the day he eats of the tree.
His soul is to some extent cut off from God who is the source of life. He's cut off from the tree of life.
And the effect that has is that it eventually brings about his physical death.
Then his soul is separated from his body until the bodily
resurrection. He defines us. Okay. So you will sometimes hear folks, orthodox and otherwise,
who are trying to defend the idea of penal substitution who will say, well, Christ died in our place
and they'll want to say, well, no, I'm talking about physical death, right? Because this is
people who accept calcedonian Christology, the claim we're making when
we say Christ died on the cross or even more provocatively God died on the cross.
The claim we're making is not that the divine nature somehow quote unquote died.
Died never never never means ceased to exist.
Right.
You notice here, right?
Never means anything like that.
What we are saying is our Lord Jesus Christ, the divine person who takes upon himself human
nature that human nature.
nature includes a human soul and a human body. And so Christ allows, because he does it voluntarily,
his human soul to be separated from his human body. That's what death is. That's what physical
death is. That's what death means for everyone. Is that your human soul is separated from your human
body? Right. And you know, I mean, it's a very natural question if people say, well, Christ died in our
and it's like well, but don't send everyone still
I, right.
And so if someone wants to say, well, that's what we're talking about.
We're talking about physical death.
I'm still going to die a physical death.
Yeah.
So there wasn't, he didn't do it in your place.
He didn't die.
He didn't do it instead of me.
I'm still going to die a physical death.
Yeah.
And that's, and we say this in the prayer that priests say often preparing for liturgy
and liturgy, right?
That Christ, human soul, separated from his human body, his human body goes into the
the tomb, his human soul descends into the...
to hero it, right? And as God, he is everywhere present and filling all things, right?
He is with the thief and paradise. He is on the throne with the Father, the Spirit,
right, etc., etc., right? That's what we're saying about Christ, okay? So for this to work,
for penal substitution to work, fundamentally, and this is the claim Calvin and the Calvinist
in this tradition make.
Christ has to experience spiritual death on the cross.
Yeah, which is the separation of the soul from God.
Right. Christ's human soul has to be separated from God.
This is what Calvin and those are the Calvinist tradition, who teach people
subsidiary Shushman, substitute share atonement, say, happened.
Yeah, and that's why you get some people will say, well, on the cross,
God turns us back on Jesus.
Right. And we're in suffered hell on...
Yeah, yeah, and then I miss
understand a misquote, you know, Christ's reference to Psalm 21 slash 22, where he's actually
referring to the whole Psalm and not just to one line.
And that claim is heretical.
Yeah.
Because I mean, what does that mean?
The father is separated from the son.
Like, what is it right about who God is?
Is he not God anymore?
Like, what's going on?
It's just nuts.
You either have to be a Trinitarian
or a crystallological heretic to hold to it.
Or you could be, or you could be William Lane Craig
and go for the hat trick.
But if you're not a Christian,
right, like William Lane Craig is not,
you could just make up a religion.
Right, and do whatever you want theologically.
And I know that sounds harsh when I say that,
but I have through a slight proxy on a life
stream, questioned William Lane Craig about this. And his argument to defend his view of penal
substitution with Christ, he appealed to the fact that he is a self-described neo-apollinarian,
a pollinarianism being a condemned heresy with his Christology. He doesn't believe Jesus has
a human soul. That was his answer to be questioning him about this, okay? So I'm not
you
being harsh, I'm taking him at his word that he's, that he's has heretical views of these
things that put him outside of Christianity according to the, not like the later ecumenical
councils that Protestants don't like, like the first one, right? Like the second one. The
ones that produce the nice and creed, the ones that supposedly all Christians agree on,
He doesn't, right?
So, but I mean, and I'm going to be
here again when you read the reformed tradition and they're talking about this
issue most of them opt to become Christological heretics in that they
basically adopt an historian Christology where Christ's humanity and
divinity are separate at least on the cross.
The Christ's humanity is in some way separated from his own
divine nature from his own Godhood in order to make this penal substitution thing work.
So this is a theological debacle.
And so to those well-meaning clergy and monastics and stuff out there, if somehow you hear this,
who go around saying things like, oh no, we accept penalism as a usually a toilet,
Because we think Christ died for us as STOP.
saying that that's not what penal substitute sharia tone meant means. Okay? You don't believe this.
We don't cosine this. Yeah. Okay. We do not think it is possible that Christ's human soul could be in
any way for any period of time separated from God. Okay? Not not possible. Not in our tradition.
And if you're paying attention to the
liturgics and let and holy weekend everything are tradition over and over again says the opposite
right
Then it's it's kind of amazing that Christ was able to be dead for as long as he was
Because it was impossible for him as God to see decay
For his soul to remain separate from his body for that long is itself
wondrous and miraculous
But he had something he was doing in harrowing Hades
They didn't fulfill the Sabbath resting in
the two, right? So we need to just leave off with this, right? We don't believe this. No
one should believe this, right? Protestants who aren't Calvinists definitely should not
believe this. And even Calvinists, someone who are coming around, right? Like you don't
need this, right? This penal substitute, Sherry Toneman, right? It's not coming out of
the Bible and it breaks the rest of your logic. It requires you to believe
things about who Christ is and about the Holy Trinity that you know are wrong in other contexts.
Right. So let's leave that off. So enough, enough negativity.
You know, I hate negativity. I hate negativity. So negative. I love to focus on the positive.
What are the positive images we get? Well, it's related to what we were talking about in the
second half, right?
We have two main positive images of what Christ does in his death and oh yeah, resurrection.
We'll get to that in a second.
And those are related to two different feasts.
Right in the Hebrew Bible.
The first one is Paska Passover.
Pesok.
Passover.
And what's happening in Passover?
Right, we've talked about this before the show show we will
We won't believe we'll believe right now. There's no people substitution going on there at all. Right?
What's going on at the Passover is manu mission people being set free from slavery in Egypt and the judgment
as
God himself says on the Passover night the judgment of the Egyptian gods
The judgment be rendered against the demonic powers and the people being set free and
And this is fulfilled in Christ filled full in that
In Christ we're not just set free from living as slaves to some Egyptians on this earth,
but we're set free from the powers of sin and death, and the judgment that's rendered
is not just against, not just the Egyptian gods being exposed as being not really gods,
but all of those dark powers being defeated once and for all.
The other feast is what we've been talking about tonight, the Day of Atonement.
And again, you go back to our Atomid episodes, nothing about people's penal substitution
going on there at all, right?
In Leviticus 16, you have two elements, expiation, sin being taken away, and the purification
and purification of the sanctuary, right?
The purification, right?
And the sins being sent, returned to sender back to their origin, back to his nasal, right?
the cosmic atonement we were talking
about in the second half is the fulfillment of that Christ accomplishes that he purifies
according to first John 2 verse 2 the whole world right that was previously under the power
of the evil one according to first John 5 right but now has been purified he defeats the
power of sin he defeats destroys the works of the evil one as first John says right and
and accomplishes this cosmic day of Atonement.
And this is summed up in a very simple phrase uttered by Saint John the
Forerunner. When he says about Christ, behold the Lamb of God who takes away
the sins of the world. Yeah, because he has pushed these together.
Yeah, Lamb of God is passive or language, taking the sins away. That's a
tonement day language. Right. These are brought together in the one person of
Christ and in his action of atonement.
which includes the cross, doesn't begin there.
Say, Nathadacious tells us it begins when he's conceived,
which we celebrated a couple days ago,
and doesn't end at the cross either.
Right, but continues into it through the resurrection,
through the ascension and his enthronement, right,
on and to his glorious appearing.
But I wanna pause for a minute to talk about,
Hey, what about the resurrection?
Because I think there is a real imbalance in Western Christian thought.
Because the questions father Andrew and I get in response to us talking about atonement.
And I'll say by the way, I know you're about to finish the sentence.
But like the YouTube chat has been lit up with exactly these kinds of questions.
Yeah.
Well, what about the cross then?
Well, what does the cross do then?
It's out of the cross.
across the cross, cross cruisive,
action the cross, the cruisive,
action.
Okay.
Um.
Where that's the central point,
that's the end all and be all right.
Like everything's accomplished right there.
It's done.
Yeah.
Which is kind of funny.
I mean,
what about the resurrection?
Yeah, I'll say by the way,
just to telegraph our next episode is going to be about the cross.
Yeah.
So, you know, come back later.
But we're going to get ready.
We're going to get ready.
We'll get right
to that question. Yeah exactly but like it's interesting you know when Jesus says it is finished
he's not dead yet. You ever notice that guys? I just want to put that out there.
And we'll talk more about that what that means next time. Yeah exactly exactly. But
but we don't stop it good Friday. Right in fact we just celebrated the Sunday of the cross and
and it's smack in the middle of length.
Yeah, yep.
Let is not preparing for the cross.
Let is not preparing for good fright.
Let is preparing for the celebration of the resurrection.
So people are stopping a little too early in their thinking.
Right?
Because when St. Paul talks about Christ's death and resurrection,
right, he sometimes refers to the cross.
when St. Paul refers to the cross.
If you read closely and follow what he's saying, the cross for him includes the whole sequence
of events.
The cross includes Christ's whole life and all the suffering and everything he endured
leading up to the actual crucifixion, but it also includes his resurrection.
And the cross part, the part about being dead, right?
part about suffering. That part we...
already got right we're already spiritually dead Israel was already dead they
were dry bones in a valley see Ezekiel yeah which we read yeah right before
Paska as part of the Holy Saturday series of yes yes already dead right we got
that part. What we're looking for is...
the renewed life, the new start, the renewal of our nature, right? The freedom that comes
on the other side, right, of Passover, of Paska, right? That's what we're looking for. That's
what we're hoping for. That's what our trust is in. That's what we're preparing to celebrate.
Right? And so if you just stop at the cross.
And try and view that as the end all and be all of atonement and
Of salvation right you're really missing a lot of the core of Christianity which actually surrounds the fact that Christ
You know I'm saying this early, but Christ is risen. He still is even when it's during that right. It's not like
He stops being risen. Right
That's at the core of the Christian Proclamation
Yeah.
Right.
All kinds of Jewish people and lots of atheists and lots of people of other religions, not Muslims, but just about everybody else acknowledges that Christ was crucified.
Let's separate these Christians as we believe he's risen.
So we should think about that a little, right?
And if our mind and our theological thinking can...
move through the crucifixion to the resurrection, we've got a blockage there that needs to be cleared
in our thinking. But that said, we'll get into the cross more next episode.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, to wrap things up briefly here at the end, I mean, I think, I think especially
in looking at this text which has this profound hope.
for the atoning of all things,
and just say the cleaning up of all things
and God's intervention and pushing the devil away
from this world and sending the sin back to him
and all this kind of stuff.
I mean, I think that that's very applicable
for this moment in human history where many of us,
maybe not the whole world,
but certainly many of us here in the West
and particularly many of us in America.
Often, at this moment, I think many of us feel
like the
is closing in around us. I hear people say all the time, the world is crazy. Whether that has
always been the case or whatever doesn't matter too much because we're having that experience.
People feel like our society is cracking. One of the reactions that I see people have is despair.
and you know despair, you know, for some people.
that leads them over the edge and they they'll take their own life or whatever. But also what despair does
is it can be nihilistic and harm other people. So despair is kind of the basis for terrorism.
You know, for mass shootings and all this kind of stuff. I mean this is why so many people who commit these
mass shootings, the last person they shoot is themselves. Because in some sense they feel that the
world has fallen to pieces that there's nothing there for them.
Christianity absolutely has critique for the world. Absolutely. Of course it has critique
for the world. But what it has more than anything else is hope. Christ didn't come into this
world to condemn it, but to save it. That is explicitly in the Scripture. Again, that
doesn't mean there's no critique. It doesn't mean that sin isn't condemned. But but
fundamentally what the message of Jesus is to the world is a message of hope, of rescue from all of this darkness, of rescue from slavery to sinful passions,
which is really about involvement with demonic powers.
And one of the things I like about the text we talked about tonight is that it makes that spiritual warfare very, very explicit.
I mean, you actually see, you know, this demonic being a zeal who is
eventually the devil in a number of these kinds of texts, you see him on the scene and
being battled against interestingly by Abraham.
Right?
Yes, God, his angels and so forth were all involved, but Abraham is the locus of all of that.
And our call is to be sons of Abraham.
Our call is to be, you know, his offspring.
Let's use the language of C.
Paul. And if we are Abraham's offspring, meaning we are, if we are the faithful, if we do as Abraham
did, then that means that we inherit the promises to become like the stars, right? To become like the
angels. Because that's what was promised to Abraham from the beginning. And that's what salvation
ultimately is is it's becoming equals the angels as Jesus says. And so I, you know, even though maybe
this is not one of the sort of the greatest hits of the apocrypha although I mean
I think this is a really interesting text.
It may not be the ones that people clamor about the most.
I still find it absolutely fascinating
and very hopeful.
It tells this story in a particular way
that I think connects with us here in the 21st century
west very well, not just in terms of the assessment
of how we feel the world is at this moment,
but also in terms of, okay, here's what we do.
Right. And you know, if you're going to image.
Abraham in this particular text, it's about offering those sacrifices, both in the literal sense of
participating in the divine liturgy, but also in the broader sense of offering ourselves as living
sacrifices, as turning over what it is that we have to God so that it can be transformed and made
salvific for us. Yeah, so I really enjoyed this discussion, and even though this is a text not
not written by a Christian.
Obviously, Christians can get a whole lot out of it a lot of beautiful beautiful stuff. So yeah, thank you
Thank you father for
For guiding this conversation. So what does it you have to say here at the end of all things
So hopefully not
I don't know that I'm ready for that all these things should be more ready than I am
Yeah, yeah
But yeah, so
I know this what I'm about to talk about.
about is something I've talked about probably even fairly recently on the show, but I find myself in real life,
meaning as a priest dealing with a group of parishioners and trying to help them and guide them and just family members and everybody in general,
I find myself having to say this over and over and over again, which tells me that probably if I say it over this microphone to people,
There's probably at least some folks out there who need to hear it again.
even if I have talked about it recently, the Christianity
that those of us at least in the United States,
and I can only speak about that experience,
because I haven't had any others.
Christianity we grew up around came from one
of two categories, largely.
And people who wanted to defend those types of Christianity
will call this a caricature.
I don't care anymore what you want to say about what I say.
But this what I'm about to say
Even if you think it's a caricature of what they're trying to teach, this is what a lot of the people within these traditions have actually received.
Right? So it's very easy to defend some tradition based on what's in the books and what's, you know, what you...
What we would mean to say, right? But I'm talking about what the people who I encounter, the people who talk to me about spiritual things, the people who come to me and give confessions,
what they've received.
from the Christianity they grew up around.
How that has shaped them, how they think because of it.
Right? And if people, representatives of those groups want to say that's not what they meant to teach.
Cool, but maybe some introspection on why that's not what people are receiving.
Anyway, what people have received comes into two categories.
One is sort of the Smiling Bob Schouler School of, God loves you just the way you are
the way you are and you don't have to do anything.
just don't worry about it. Just smile and be happy and listen to the hymns of your choice that you
enjoy. Right. That worked, I'm going to again be very blunt. That worked really well with boomers.
That seemed to answer something they needed to hear. Maybe their generation who grew up with very
dissatisfied perfectionist parents and so just hearing you're fine just the way you are was
what they needed, right? But that...
That doesn't work on subsequent generations
because subsequent generations are more realistic
or nihilistic depending on your point of view.
And no, there's something deeply wrong
with themselves and with the world around them.
So just telling them over again,
no, no, you're fine, everything's fine,
it doesn't work, right?
That's why those kind of churches are all empty now.
The other school of thought is pretty much the exact opposite.
Good.
God doesn't really love you.
Right.
In fact, he's pretty angry with you.
And he's getting ready to send you to hell.
Right?
And the only way to avoid that is
depending on your tradition, right, is
for you to love him nonetheless really sincerely,
And there's a rabbit hole to go down.
House...
sincere MI ever really. And or do that plus live your life at a certain way and follow certain rules,
which will differ based on tradition, and which you will inevitably fail at.
That second one is most of the people who I interact with on spiritual matters.
And it's almost like they've been...
taught and they've internalized that their life in this world is this sort of really horrible
reality show, almost like squid game.
And like God is about weeding out contestants and narrowing it down to this faithful few.
And everybody else goes to hell, goes to eternal punishment, except for this faithful few
Who again, depending on...
on your tradition, he may just pick. Or, you know, they're the ones who really did it right.
They're the ones who really loved him sincerely. Or they're the ones who really lived their
life the right way. And anyway, you slice those things. Most people, again, are realistic
enough that when they look at their life, they don't see a lot of evidence in their life
and their actions that they're one of the people got picked.
Or they don't see a lot of evidence of their life that they're really sincere about following God.
Or they don't see a lot of evidence of their life that they're really towing the line and living the life they know they should be living.
Meaning most people are walking around, like religious people, walking around thinking they're probably going to end up in hell.
That God is probably bad at the most of the time.
and that he's looking for them to make some misstep. So boom, they can get nailed.
Also most atheists are walking around doing the same thing. They're protesting constantly that there is no God
because they can't deal with that guilt and stuff that they've internalized. They can't live like that.
that. No one can live like that. But they're out to trying to live like that.
and deal with the cognitive distance is just to deny that any of it's true.
Over and over and over again publicly loudly to everyone who will listen.
Right.
Whereas the religious people are just in this kind of quiet desperation of how do I figure
this out.
Right.
So, let me reiterate again, right.
And penal substitute should play a big part in this.
That's why I'm bringing it up in this context.
God loves you.
Jesus said so.
Say John's Gospel.
The Father Himself loves you.
He is not angry at you.
He does not want to destroy you for your sins.
There is no power of justice that commands Him to do so.
No one commands Him to do anything.
He loves you.
He wants you to find salvation.
But salvation is a thing you have to actually do.
wants you to do it. The
Bible says so, God wills that all men be saved and come to the knowledge of the truth.
But you have to do it.
He empowers you to do it.
He forgives you when you mess up trying to do it.
He heals you when you damage yourself trying to do it in failing.
He is entirely on your side.
The God who created the universe is entirely on your side and the saints are on your side
And the church is on your side
Everyone is on your side
Right Christ is advocating for you
Everything is set up for us
When Saint Paul says to us continue to work out your salvation with fear and trembling
You don't stop there like Kierkegaard did
Read the next verse because it is God who is working in you to will and to do according to his pleasure.
We continue on and we work out our salvation because we know that God is on our side and empowering us to do it and loving us and loving other people through us.
We need to pray about that.
We need to pray it.
We need to repeat it. We need to kind of imitate what the atheists are doing. We need to say it out loud. We need to say it to each other. We need to say it to everyone who will listen.
Right.
That God loves you and wants you to find salvation, wants you to be healed, wants you to be set free from sin. He wants all these things for you.
It doesn't mean you have nothing to do. That doesn't mean you're fine just the way you are. You know you're not fine just the way you are.
Right.
but it means that he is there to help you to grow, to be transformed into the person who
you need to be and want to be.
The person he created you to be for eternity.
That's the actual message of Christianity.
Don't accept any substitutes for that.
Ever at all for any reason.
That's what I have to say.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight, everyone.
Thank you very much for listening.
you didn't happen to get through to a slide.
We'd select to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of Spirits and www.engedfate.com.
You can message our Facebook page. You can leave us a voice message at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
If you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish because that is where we live this life.
Head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
I sailed the sea of desolation and dropped my anchor there.
I climbed the depths of isolation, walked its way...
think it was not scared.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings,
and share the show with a friend who's going to benefit from it.
I'll probably be sure to go to www.agspacet.com.stokesupport
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasts stay on the air.
Went from end to end to end.
And then from there I went again,
the road that only this one knows,
off to nowhere, here I go.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice, worthy is the
and that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.